<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Homeworks | Applied Longitudinal Data Analysis</title>
    <link>/homeworks/</link>
      <atom:link href="/homeworks/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Homeworks</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Homeworks</title>
      <link>/homeworks/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Homework #2</title>
      <link>/homeworks/homework-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/homeworks/homework-2/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Submit homework Rmd and pdf file to: &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:Homewor.c9u2tv5bm4mb6nbs@u.box.com&#34; class=&#34;email&#34;&gt;Homewor.c9u2tv5bm4mb6nbs@u.box.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using example data set 4 from workshop #3 (Multiple Waves, Different Variables ), to answer the following questions. There are 7 waves of data. There are five different types of repeated measures variables, all from “the Big Five” of personality. Each of these five constructs have 9 items associated with them. See codebook for more details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Create composites of each of the 5 constructs and run growth models on each of these composite constructs. Include varying intercept and slopes for each of the five models. Bonus points for doing so in purrr. Interpret the parameters for 1 of the models that you are interested in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Introduce age and sex as predictors to the slope and intercept to the same model you interpreted in #1. Interpret each of the parameters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Use the output to create a table, suitable for publication in a journal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plot the predicted fixed effects along with the random effects on the same plot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Introduce one of the remaining 4 repeated measures as a time varying covariate (tvc) at level 1. First, run the model where the time varying covariate is constrained to be equal for everyone. Interpret the parameters of your model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Run a second tvc model where the new repeated measure is allowed to vary randomly across people. Interpret. Then compare this one with the one where it is constrained to be equal using a likelihood ratio test. Interpret.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>homework #1</title>
      <link>/homeworks/homework-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/homeworks/homework-1/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Answer the questions below using your own data (for question 1) and the dataset from this file for the remaining questions:&lt;a href=&#34;https://raw.github.com/josh-jackson/ALDA/master/Hw1&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://raw.github.com/josh-jackson/ALDA/master/Hw1&lt;/a&gt; If you have your own longitudinal data, please feel free to use that instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If using the provided dataset note that we are looking at depression across 5 waves during college. Waves are signified by a letter at the start of the variable name, starting with A, then B, then C, etcetera. Not all waves collected depression during college.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please email your answers via a) an Rmd file and b) a pdf to: &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:Homewor.dk7huzwn6n5aohka@u.box.com&#34; class=&#34;email&#34;&gt;Homewor.dk7huzwn6n5aohka@u.box.com&lt;/a&gt; If you are using your own data please also attach the dataset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Create a codebook with an actual dataset you are working with (it does not need to be longitudinal). Feed it into R to change variable names.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Take a wide dataset (such as the provided one) and make it long&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Run separate linear models on all of the participants subjects (a basic regression). What is the average intercept, the average slope?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now run a mlm/lmer model with only a random intercept. What is the ICC? Interpret.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Introduce a fixed slope term. What is the difference in interpretation for the fixed effects estimates in this estimate and the previous? Of the residual standard error?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Run an additional model with a random slope. How does this change compare to the previous fixed slope model? Should you keep the random slope or not?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Interpret the correlation between the slope and the intercept.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Create a density plot of the random effects from your final model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
