<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Lectures | Applied Longitudinal Data Analysis</title>
    <link>/lectures/</link>
      <atom:link href="/lectures/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Lectures</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Lectures</title>
      <link>/lectures/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 1</title>
      <link>/lectures/02-lda-basics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/lectures/02-lda-basics/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div id=&#34;TOC&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#lda-basics&#34;&gt;LDA basics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#procedural&#34;&gt;Procedural&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#goals&#34;&gt;Goals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#motivation-terms-concepts&#34;&gt;Motivation, terms, concepts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#why-longitudinal-what-can-we-ask&#34;&gt;Why longitudinal? What can we ask?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#types-of-change-most-common&#34;&gt;Types of change (most common)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#between-person-versus-within-person-variables&#34;&gt;Between person versus within person variables&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#modeling-frameworks-mlm-sem&#34;&gt;Modeling frameworks: MLM &amp;amp; SEM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#meaningful-time-metric&#34;&gt;Meaningful time metric&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#thinking-through-longitudinal-data-example&#34;&gt;Thinking through longitudinal data example&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#person-level&#34;&gt;Person level&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#doing-this-with-mlm-and-sem&#34;&gt;Doing this with MLM (and SEM)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#design-considerations&#34;&gt;Design considerations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#number-of-assessment-waves&#34;&gt;1. Number of assessment waves&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#measurement&#34;&gt;2. Measurement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#threats-to-validity&#34;&gt;Threats to validity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#missing-data&#34;&gt;1. Missing data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#attritionmortality&#34;&gt;2. Attrition/Mortality&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#historycohort&#34;&gt;3. History/cohort&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#maturation&#34;&gt;4. Maturation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#testing&#34;&gt;5. Testing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#selection&#34;&gt;6. Selection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#why-not-rm-anova&#34;&gt;Why not RM ANOVA?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;lda-basics&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;LDA basics&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;procedural&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Procedural&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By virtue of being on this page, you know the class website. You may access all of the code and datasets and everything that is used to create the lectures through my github: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/josh-jackson/ALDA&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://github.com/josh-jackson/ALDA&lt;/a&gt;. The provided code should be enough but if you want to search farther go for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;goals&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This first class is set to orientate you to the world of longitudinal data and MLM models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;motivation-terms-concepts&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Motivation, terms, concepts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;why-longitudinal-what-can-we-ask&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why longitudinal? What can we ask?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least 7 reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Identification of intraindividual change (and stability). Do people increase or decrease with time or age. Is this pattern monotonic? Should this best be conceptualized as a stable process or something that is more dynamic? On average how do people change? Ex: people decline in cognitive ability across time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Inter-individual differences in intraindividual change. Does everyone change the same? Do some people start higher but change less? Do some increase while some decrease? Ex: not all people people decline in cognitive ability across time, but some do.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Examine joint relationship among intraindividual change for two or more constructs. If variable X goes up does variable Y also go up across time? Does this always happen or only during certain times? Is this association due to a third variable or does it mean that change occurs for similar reasons? Ex: changes in cognitive ability are associated with changes in health across time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Determinants of intraindividual change. What are the repeated experiences that can push construct X around. Do these have similar effects at all times? Ex: people declinein cognitive ability across time. Ex: I have better memory compared to other times when I engage in cognitive activities vs times that I do not.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Determinants of interindividual differences in intraindividual change. Do events, background characteristics, interventions or other between person characteristic shape why certain people change while others don’t? Ex: people decline less in cognitive ability across time if tend to do cognitively engaging activities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Inter-individual differences in intraindividual fluctuation and determinants of intraindividual fluctuation. Does everyone vary the same? Why are some more variable than others? Ex: Someone who is depressed fluctuates more in happiness than someone who is not depressed&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Are there different classes/populations/mixtures of intraindividual change? Ex: do people who decrease vs don’t in cognitive ability across time exist as different groups? (Vs construing differences as on a continuum).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;types-of-change-most-common&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Types of change (most common)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many ways to think of change and stability. We will only have time to go into a few of these types, but it is helpful to think about what type you are interested in when you plan a project or sit down to analyze data. “Change” can mean different things. The above questions you can ask mostly map onto #3 definition of change below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Differential / rank order consistency/ rank order stability. Goes by many names but in the end it is just a correlation. This is a group/sample/population level variable and indexes the relative standing of a person with regard to the rest of the members in the sample. Does not take into account mean structure. Best used with heterotypic continuity where the construct may be the same but the measurement of the construct changes e.g., childhood IQ or acting out in school versus when you are an adult.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A specialized case of this is ipsative change, which looks at the rank order of constructs within a person. This is not done on a single variable (depression) but on a broad number of them (all PD symptoms). Often uses profiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mean level/ absolute change. Takes into account mean structure and indexes absolute levels of a construct. A strong assumption is that the construct means (not a pun) the same thing across time. That is, my measure of depression is interpreted the same for a 40 year old and a 90 year old if I want to look at absolute differences between the two ages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mean level change is not dependent at all on rank order consistency. Can have no mean level change and high rank order consistency and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Individual differences in change. Rank order and mean level provide an index of change and or stability for the sample. Here this provides an assessment of change for an individual. For example, if it is typical to decline in cognitive ability do some people buck the trend and stay at their past level? Individual differences in change get at both mean level changes as well as the tendency of the sample to show stability. It is the type of change that we will focus on the most.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Structural. Does the construct (or measure) change across time? The assumption for mean level change assumes that the measurement properties stays the same. But maybe it is theoretically interesting to ask whether what you are measuring changes. Examples include practice effects, age effects (cog ability in kids vs adults), differences due to health and life events.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Variance. Does your experiment lead to an increas in variability in response? You may show no mean levels (which is what is looked at in typical t-tests and ANOVAs) but you could see people increase or decrease in their expected range of response.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how do we refer to ‘change’? Usually it is easier to refer to pictorially or in terms of an equation. Putting a word onto it usually causes some confusion, which is why there are a lot of redundant terms in the literature. All of these might refer to the same thing when used within a model. However, the names of some models use these terms differently and thus can refer to different models or conditions that you are working with. In this class I will try to point out the important differences but you will be fine if you supplement your terms with graphs or equations. Math is the great equalizer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;between-person-versus-within-person-variables&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Between person versus within person variables&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between-person versus within-person are the shortened version of interindividaul differences in change versus intraindividaul differences in change. Refers to across people versus within a particular person. Do you care about how people differ from their previous and future self or do you care about how people differ from other people? (See examples in the 7 types of questions we can ask)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often we are interested in modeling both between person and within person variables simultaneously. This is related to Level 1 and Level 2 (for those of you familiar with this terminology). It is helpful to start thinking about what variables you are working with and whether they are within or between person variables. For predictors, it is typically the case that between person effects are constant (between person) variables (e.g., gender) that do not change from assessment to assessment or are only assessed once. In contrast, within person questions are best understood by time varying predictors (within person variables e.g., daily mood) that are assessed more than once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will incorporate both time invariant (between person) and time varying (within person) predictors into our eventual model. In addition to thinking about the types of questions you want to ask it is important to think about what “type” or variables you are working with. Your choice of questions you can ask depends on how often you assess variables or how you conceptualize them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;modeling-frameworks-mlm-sem&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Modeling frameworks: MLM &amp;amp; SEM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this class (and in the field) two primary techniques are used with longitudinal models: MLM and SEM. At some levels they are completely equivalent. At others, one is better than the other and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MLM/HLM is a simple extension of standard regression models. As a result it is easy to interpret and implement. In terms of longitudinal data it is best suited to run models when the time of measurement differs from person to person (compared to equal intervals). For this class we will use lme4 and brms as our MLM program but there are many others we could use e.g., nlme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SEM is related to regression in that regression is a subset of SEM techniques. In other words, an SEM program could run a simple regression analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary advantage of MLM is that you may have assessment waves that vary in length between participants. An assumption of SEM models is that everyone has the same amount of time between assessment waves (though this assumption can be relaxed). MLM is also better suited for complex error structures and complex nesting above and beyond assessments within person. It is also easier to model interactions. Currently, it is easier to do MLM within a Bayesian framework too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SEM primary advantage is the ability to account for measurement error via latent assessment of the repeated measures. Other advantages include the ability to model multiple DVs at once, and do so in a flexible manner to look at, for example, the associations between change in one construct and change in the another (though these are also possible with MLMs). Another major advantage is the ability to look at latent groups via latent class or mixture models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bottom line: MLM is probably best suited for “basic” or “standard” growth models. More complex analyses of change with multiple variables would benefit from an SEM approach. This is also an oversimplification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;meaningful-time-metric&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Meaningful time metric&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time is the most important part of a longitudinal analyses. Without some sort of explicit operationalization of time or thought into how you handle time in your analyses you are not conducting longitudinal analyses. The key to interpreting your output is to know how you handled your time variable. What units is it in? Does everyone have the same differences between assessments? Is time something you are explicitly interested in or merely there as a means to collect repeated measures? We will discuss more of these as the semester progresses. Right now however an important distinction is what should the scale of our x-axis variable, time, be in?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At one level, the distinction is relevant to what is the process that is changing someone? Is it a naturally occurring developmental process? Then maybe age is the best metric. What about tracking child’s cognitive ability, something that might be influenced by level of schooling? Here grade may be more important than age. Another common metric is time in study. This may be useful if you are running an intervention or if you want to put everyone on the same starting metric and then control for nuisance variables like age or schooling level. Similarly, year of study as a prime time candidate may be useful if you are working from panel studies and interested in historical events and or cohort effects. A wave variable (ie study measurement occasion) may be good enough to use as a time metric (though this makes some assumptions about the regularity of assessments both within and across people).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on your choice of time metric you may see different rates of change and variability in change. For psychological applications the most common would be age and time in study (followed by grades for assessments of kids). Age is nice because it captures a number of developmental processes thought to drive change (maturation, history, time-in-study) but does not identify a single reason. Time in study is the opposite in that it does not index any other type of change but that simplicity aides in testing different reasons for change (e.g, age moderation). Thus choosing one type of time metric will naturally guide the types of questions you are able to address. E.g. if you use age as your time metric you won’t be able to control for age or examine the effects of age as simply as if you used time in study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;thinking-through-longitudinal-data-example&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thinking through longitudinal data example&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(ggplot2)
library(tidyverse)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## ── Attaching packages ─────────────────────────── tidyverse 1.2.1.9000 ──&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## ✔ tibble  2.1.3           ✔ dplyr   0.8.3      
## ✔ tidyr   0.8.99.9000     ✔ stringr 1.4.0      
## ✔ readr   1.3.1           ✔ forcats 0.4.0      
## ✔ purrr   0.3.2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## ── Conflicts ─────────────────────────────────── tidyverse_conflicts() ──
## ✖ dplyr::filter() masks stats::filter()
## ✖ dplyr::lag()    masks stats::lag()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using some resting state imaging data, lets think about how we can model and think about this data using our current skills (ie standard regression and plotting)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We defined time as year in study. How would this look if we used age?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;gg1 &amp;lt;- ggplot(example,
   aes(x = year, y = SMN7, group = ID)) + geom_point()  
print(gg1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning: Removed 9 rows containing missing values (geom_point).&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Lectures/02-LDA-basics_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-5-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above graph just plots datapoints. Do we have repeated assessments per person? Lets find out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;person-level&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Person level&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;gg2 &amp;lt;- ggplot(example,
   aes(x = year, y = SMN7, group = ID)) + geom_line()  
gg2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning: Removed 9 rows containing missing values (geom_path).&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Lectures/02-LDA-basics_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-6-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;
Note that some people start at different levels. Some people have more data in terms of assessment points and years. Note that the shape of change isn’t necessarily a straight line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We often want to look at this at a per person level to get more info.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;gg3 &amp;lt;- ggplot(example,
   aes(x = year, y = SMN7, group = ID)) + geom_line() +  geom_point() + facet_wrap( ~ ID)
gg3&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning: Removed 9 rows containing missing values (geom_path).&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning: Removed 9 rows containing missing values (geom_point).&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Lectures/02-LDA-basics_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-7-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;
As part of our dataset we have different groups. A question we may have is if they change differently across time. Lets take a look at this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;gg4 &amp;lt;- ggplot(example,
   aes(x = year, y = SMN7, group = ID)) + geom_line() + facet_grid(. ~ group)
gg4&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning: Removed 9 rows containing missing values (geom_path).&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Lectures/02-LDA-basics_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-8-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re not in Kansas anymore - look at the technocolor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;gg5 &amp;lt;-  gg2 + aes(colour = factor(ID)) + guides(colour=FALSE) 
gg5&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning: Removed 9 rows containing missing values (geom_path).&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Lectures/02-LDA-basics_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-9-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, beside the occular technique, we’re going to need to do something more to address our theoretical questions. Lets look at some random people in the sample and run some regressions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;set.seed(11)
ex.random &amp;lt;- example %&amp;gt;% 
  dplyr::select(ID) %&amp;gt;% 
  distinct %&amp;gt;% 
  sample_n(10) 

example2 &amp;lt;-
  left_join(ex.random, example)  &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Joining, by = &amp;quot;ID&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;gg6 &amp;lt;- ggplot(example2,
   aes(x = week, y = SMN7, group = ID)) +  geom_point() + stat_smooth(method=&amp;quot;lm&amp;quot;) + facet_wrap( ~ID)
gg6&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning in qt((1 - level)/2, df): NaNs produced

## Warning in qt((1 - level)/2, df): NaNs produced

## Warning in qt((1 - level)/2, df): NaNs produced

## Warning in qt((1 - level)/2, df): NaNs produced

## Warning in qt((1 - level)/2, df): NaNs produced

## Warning in qt((1 - level)/2, df): NaNs produced&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Lectures/02-LDA-basics_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-10-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets look at individual level regressions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(tidyverse)
library(broom)

regressions &amp;lt;- example2 %&amp;gt;% 
  group_by(ID) %&amp;gt;% 
  do(tidy(lm(SMN7 ~ week, data=.)))

regressions&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## # A tibble: 20 x 6
## # Groups:   ID [10]
##       ID term        estimate std.error statistic  p.value
##    &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt;          &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;     &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;     &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;    &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;
##  1    67 (Intercept)  0.0921    0.0161      5.72    0.0292
##  2    67 week         0.00662   0.00657     1.01    0.420 
##  3    75 (Intercept)  0.126   NaN         NaN     NaN     
##  4    75 week         0.00771 NaN         NaN     NaN     
##  5    87 (Intercept)  0.0787  NaN         NaN     NaN     
##  6    87 week        -0.0227  NaN         NaN     NaN     
##  7    99 (Intercept)  0.111     0.0236      4.69    0.0426
##  8    99 week         0.00545   0.0122      0.446   0.699 
##  9   101 (Intercept)  0.111     0.0424      2.62    0.232 
## 10   101 week         0.0421    0.0217      1.94    0.303 
## 11   103 (Intercept)  0.0887  NaN         NaN     NaN     
## 12   103 week        -0.0168  NaN         NaN     NaN     
## 13   105 (Intercept)  0.0465    0.00658     7.06    0.0896
## 14   105 week         0.00122   0.00467     0.261   0.838 
## 15   142 (Intercept)  0.197   NaN         NaN     NaN     
## 16   142 week         0.0130  NaN         NaN     NaN     
## 17   149 (Intercept)  0.0801  NaN         NaN     NaN     
## 18   149 week         0.00497 NaN         NaN     NaN     
## 19   152 (Intercept)  0.0921  NaN         NaN     NaN     
## 20   152 week        -0.0172  NaN         NaN     NaN&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What can we see? Estimates give us an intercept and regression coefficient for each person. Some people increase across time, some decrease. Some we cannot do statistical tests on – why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well that is per person. Lets get the average starting value and change per week&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;regressions %&amp;gt;% 
  group_by(term) %&amp;gt;% 
  summarise(avg.reg = mean(estimate))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## # A tibble: 2 x 2
##   term        avg.reg
##   &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt;         &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;
## 1 (Intercept) 0.102  
## 2 week        0.00244&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets plot the average trend across everyone. Start with a best fit line not taking into account that people have repeated measures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;gg7 &amp;lt;-  gg1 &amp;lt;- ggplot(example, aes(x = year, y = SMN7)) + geom_point() + stat_smooth() 
gg7&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## `geom_smooth()` using method = &amp;#39;loess&amp;#39; and formula &amp;#39;y ~ x&amp;#39;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning: Removed 9 rows containing non-finite values (stat_smooth).&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning: Removed 9 rows containing missing values (geom_point).&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Lectures/02-LDA-basics_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-13-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That lowess line is a little strange. How about a linear estimate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Split up by group&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;gg8 &amp;lt;-  ggplot(example, aes(x = year, y = SMN7)) + geom_point() + stat_smooth(method = &amp;quot;lm&amp;quot;) + facet_grid(. ~ group)
gg8&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning: Removed 9 rows containing non-finite values (stat_smooth).&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning: Removed 9 rows containing missing values (geom_point).&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Lectures/02-LDA-basics_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-14-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I also want to see the individual slopes, not just the average.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;gg9 &amp;lt;- ggplot(example, aes(x = year, y = SMN7, group = ID)) + geom_point(alpha = 0.05) + stat_smooth(method = &amp;quot;lm&amp;quot;, se = FALSE)   

gg10 &amp;lt;- gg9 +  stat_smooth(data = example, aes(x = year, y = SMN7, group=1, color = &amp;quot;black&amp;quot;), method = &amp;quot;lm&amp;quot;, size = 2) + guides(fill=FALSE)


gg11 &amp;lt;- gg10 + facet_grid(.~ group) + theme(legend.position=&amp;quot;none&amp;quot;)

gg11&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning: Removed 9 rows containing non-finite values (stat_smooth).

## Warning: Removed 9 rows containing non-finite values (stat_smooth).&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning: Removed 9 rows containing missing values (geom_point).&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Lectures/02-LDA-basics_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-15-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;doing-this-with-mlm-and-sem&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Doing this with MLM (and SEM)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These regressions and plots are how you should begin to think about longitudinal data analysis. These growth models (the simplest form of longitudinal data analysis) are just a bunch of regressions for each person plus a little extra stuff. MLM is just a fancy regression equation. We want to create a line for everyone. Does someone go up? Does someone go down? On average, do people’s lines indciate that this construct increases or decreases? That is it. Seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is different from normal regression? Extra error terms, mostly. For regression, we think of error as existing in one big bucket. For MLMs (and other longitudinal models) we will be breaking up unexplained variance (error) into multiple buckets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where fixed effects and random effects come into play. We will discuss this more next class, but the gist is that fixed effects are the regression coefficients you are used to. Fixed effects index group level change. Do people decline in memory across time, on average? Random effects vary among individuals (in the longitudinal models we are talking about) and index variation from the group. While most people decline in their memory, does everyone? In other words, an average trajectory will be termed a fixed effect and the random effect indexes how much variability there is around that group level effect. This extra variability we measure through random effects means that we are explaining more variance and thus there is less unexplained variance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;design-considerations&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Design considerations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;number-of-assessment-waves&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1. Number of assessment waves&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember high school algebra: two points define a line. But, that assumes we can measure constructs without error. Three assessment points will better define changes in psychological variables. As a default, you need three waves of data to use MLM models. However, some simplifications can be made with MLM. Two wave assessments are mostly better with SEM approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;measurement&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2. Measurement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;scale-of-measurement&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Scale of measurement&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Measurement is always the basis for good quantiative analysis. Without good measurement you are just spitting into the wind. Standard measurement concerns remain (reliability, dimensionality) but extra concerns exist with longitudinal data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does it mean for categorical variables to change over time? Can you imagine a trajectory for what this is measuring? How would dichotomous responses impact ability to measure change?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What about ranks, such as in preference for school subjects? What if the class composition changes – what is this assessing? Given that ranks are related such that if I increase someone has to decrease, how does that impact change assessments?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can I analyze childhood and adult variables simultaneously if assess the same construct, even though they may be measured differently? How can you measure change in the same construct but with different measures? To assess math ability in 5 year olds you can ask them about addition, can you do that in a sample of 20 year olds? Does that measure continue to assess math ability?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often the answer to these is to use a different form of the longitudinal model. In general, the better measured the construct (continuous, not dependent on others, using the same scale) the more complex/sophisticated analysis you can run. Worse measurment leads to simplification both in terms of the models and the types of conclusions you can make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with all of science, everything rests on measurement. Poor measurement results in poor conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;standardizing&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Standardizing&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is standard practice to z-score to get standardized responses. However, it is not straight forward to do so when using longitudinal data. Why would z-scoring your variables be problematic?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, if you scale for age, for example, this takes out a potential explanatory variable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, more worriesome, it also can add error if not everyone is standardized consistently (say if standardization is across age groups and someone just misses a cut). Or if the sample changes due to attrition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, is that you take away the mean for each assessment such that the expected change across time is zero. We will talk more about solutions to this problem as the semester progresses but the short answer is to avoid or to use SEM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While helpful for cross sectional analyses, z-scoring adds in layers of computational and interpretational problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;reliability&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Reliability&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of longitudinal analyses is to understand why some construct changes or stays the same across time. A major difficulty in addressing this goal is whether you are able to accurately assess the construct of interest. One of the key characteristics (but not the only characteristic) is whether or not your assessment would be consistent if you gave an alternative measure or if you retook it immediately after your first assessment. This is known as reliability of measurement. To the extent that your measure is reliable it assesses true score variance as opposed to error variance. The amount of error score variance assessed is important given that error variance will masquerade as change across time given that error can correlate with anything else. The more error in your measurement the more change you will find. Of course this is unreliable change – change that is not true change, just stochastic noise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can think of reliability two ways. First, reliability of the change estimate. This depends on how much error there is in the assessment and the number of waves. These two components are similar to inter item correlation and number of items being the two main components that effect reliability in cross sectional analyses. Increase the number of items (waves) you increase your alpha. Increase the average correlation among items, you increase your alpha. The parallel to average correlation among items is our ability to accurately assess the construct. When comparing a construct across time we examine this with measurement invariance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;measurement-invariance&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Measurement invariance&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second way to think of reliability is in terms of how consistently the measure is assessed across time. Or, do you assess the same construct at each time? What would happen if we looked at change in IQ from 1st grade to 12 grade and used the first grade IQ test at each time? The construct that you assessed at the first wave is likely not the same assessed later.
To test this formally is called measurement invariance and is typically done through SEM. We will talk more about this later in the semester. Until we get there we make a large assumption that what we are measuring now is the same at each wave of assessment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;threats-to-validity&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Threats to validity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;missing-data&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1. Missing data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;types-of-missing-data&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Types of missing data&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a scale from 1 to you’re completely screwed, how confident are you that the missingness is not related to your study variables?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Missing completely at random (MCAR) means that the missingness pattern is due entirely to randomness&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Missing at random (MAR) means that there is conditional randomness. Missingness may be due to other variables in the dataset. Pretty standard for longitudinal data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not missing at random (NMAR) means that the missingness is systematic based on the missing values and not associated with measured variables. For example, in a study of reading ability, kids with low reading ability drop out, due to not liking to take tests on reading ability. However, if reading ability is associated with other variables in the model, then this missingness becomes closer in kind to MAR, and thus somewhat less problematic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typically, we make the assumption we are working under MAR and thus we will have unbiased estimates when predictors of missingness are incorporated into the model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are tests to distinguish MAR from NMAR but you cannot distinguish MCAR from MAR because it is based entirely on knowing something that you dont have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;how-to-handle-missing-data&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;How to handle missing data&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listwise? Nah&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Full information maximum likelihood and other ML approaches? Sure.
Multiple imputation? Cannot hurt. More on these approaches later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;attritionmortality&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2. Attrition/Mortality&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Major contributor to missing data&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;historycohort&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3. History/cohort&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Know that the processes driving change can be due to a specific event or cohort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;maturation&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4. Maturation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Change may occur because of natural processes. Thus if you just follow someone across time they will likely change irregardless of say, if they are in the control group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;testing&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;5. Testing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having people take the same survey, test or interview multiple times may lead them to respond differently. Does that change result from development or does it result from them being familiar with the test?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;selection&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;6. Selection&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are looking at life events, know that life events are not distributed randomly. Moreover, people who stay in studies and even sign up for studies are different from those that do not. As a result, it is often hard to make internally valid inferences with longitudinal data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;why-not-rm-anova&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why not RM ANOVA?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cannot handle missing data&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assumes rate of change is the same for all individuals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Time is usually done with orthogonal polynomials, making it difficult to interpret or to model non-linear. In other words, you have flexibility on how you want to model time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Accounting for correlation across time uses up many parameters, MLM is more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Can accommodate differences in time between assessment waves across participants&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Handles various types of predictors - continuous vs nominal &amp;amp; static vs dynamic&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bottom line: this is an old way of doing these analyses with no upside. Don’t do them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 2</title>
      <link>/lectures/03-growth-curves/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/lectures/03-growth-curves/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div id=&#34;TOC&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#growth-curves&#34;&gt;Growth curves&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#between-person-models-and-cross-sectional-data&#34;&gt;Between person models and cross sectional data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#within-person-models-e.g.-2-level-models&#34;&gt;Within person models e.g., 2-level models&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#thinking-about-random-effects&#34;&gt;Thinking about random effects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#random-effects&#34;&gt;Random effects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#empty-model-equation&#34;&gt;Empty model equation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#putting-it-together&#34;&gt;Putting it together&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#visualize-what-you-are-doing&#34;&gt;Visualize what you are doing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#icc&#34;&gt;ICC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#adding-time&#34;&gt;Adding time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-does-this-look-like-graphically&#34;&gt;What does this look like graphically?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#adding-a-random-slope&#34;&gt;Adding a random slope?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#individaul-level-random-effects&#34;&gt;Individaul level random effects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#calculation-of-individaul-level-random-effects&#34;&gt;Calculation of individaul level random effects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#how-are-these-random-effects-calculated&#34;&gt;How are these random effects calculated?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#random-effects-and-residual-standard-assumptions&#34;&gt;random effects and residual (standard) assumptions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#random-effect-decomposition&#34;&gt;Random effect decomposition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#working-with-models-in-r&#34;&gt;working with models in R&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#data-analysis-and-data-structures&#34;&gt;Data analysis and data structures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#wide-and-long-form&#34;&gt;Wide and Long form&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#basic-lmer-code&#34;&gt;basic lmer code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#example&#34;&gt;Example&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#how-to-calculate-icc&#34;&gt;How to calculate ICC?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#exploring-beyond-the-summary&#34;&gt;Exploring beyond the summary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-do-the-random-effects-look-like&#34;&gt;what do the random effects look like?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#adding-time-to-the-mlm&#34;&gt;Adding time to the MLM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fixed-slope&#34;&gt;fixed slope&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#random-slope&#34;&gt;Random slope&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#random-effects-1&#34;&gt;Random effects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#calcualtion-of-random-effect-confidence-interval&#34;&gt;Calcualtion of random effect confidence interval&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#adding-time-1&#34;&gt;adding time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#caterpillar-plots&#34;&gt;caterpillar plots&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#density-of-individaul-random-effects&#34;&gt;Density of individaul random effects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#comparing-to-a-standard-linear-model&#34;&gt;comparing to a standard linear model&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#other-types-of-models&#34;&gt;Other types of models&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#matrix-notation-as-a-way-to-help-understand-what-is-going-on&#34;&gt;Matrix notation (as a way to help understand what is going on)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#estimation&#34;&gt;Estimation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#testing-significance-adapted-from-ben-bolker&#34;&gt;Testing significance (adapted from Ben Bolker)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#p-values-are-not-included&#34;&gt;P values are not included&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#likelhiood-ratio-test&#34;&gt;Likelhiood ratio test&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#likelihood-tests-for-random-effects&#34;&gt;Likelihood tests for random effects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#aic-and-bic&#34;&gt;AIC and BIC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#mcmc&#34;&gt;MCMC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#bootstraps&#34;&gt;Bootstraps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#predictions-and-prediction-intervals&#34;&gt;Predictions and prediction intervals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#predictions-and-prediction-intervals-1&#34;&gt;Predictions and prediction intervals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#coefficient-of-determination-equivalents&#34;&gt;Coefficient of determination equivalents&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#batch-analyses&#34;&gt;batch analyses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;growth-curves&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Growth curves&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;between-person-models-and-cross-sectional-data&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Between person models and cross sectional data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You already know this, but it gives us a chance to review regression&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ {Y}_{i} = b_{0} + b_{1}X_{1} + b_{2}X_{2} + b_{3}X_{3}+... +\epsilon_{i} \]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ \hat{Y}_{i} = b_{0} + b_{1}X_{1} + b_{2}X_{2} + b_{3}X_{3}+... \]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parameters are considered fixed where one regression value corresponds to everyone. I.e., that association between X1 and Y is the same for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each person has a Y, denoted by the subscript i, and each has a residual associated with them, also designated by i.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(readr)
example &amp;lt;- read_csv(&amp;quot;~/Box/5165 Applied Longitudinal Data Analysis/Longitudinal/example.csv&amp;quot;)
example$ID &amp;lt;- as.factor(example$ID)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets look at some data. These data examine older adults who came into a study up to six times over a six year period. Multiple cognitive, psychiatric and imaging assessments were done. Let’s look at functional connectivity network called SMN7.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(tidyverse)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## ── Attaching packages ─────────────────────────── tidyverse 1.2.1.9000 ──&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## ✔ ggplot2 3.2.1           ✔ dplyr   0.8.3      
## ✔ tibble  2.1.3           ✔ stringr 1.4.0      
## ✔ tidyr   0.8.99.9000     ✔ forcats 0.4.0      
## ✔ purrr   0.3.2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## ── Conflicts ─────────────────────────────────── tidyverse_conflicts() ──
## ✖ dplyr::filter() masks stats::filter()
## ✖ dplyr::lag()    masks stats::lag()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(ggplot2)
gg1 &amp;lt;- ggplot(example,
   aes(x = week, y = SMN7)) + geom_point() + stat_smooth(method = &amp;quot;lm&amp;quot;)   
print(gg1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Lectures/03-Growth-curves_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-2-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happens if we run a regression?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;regression &amp;lt;- lm(SMN7 ~ week, data = example)
summary(regression)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## 
## Call:
## lm(formula = SMN7 ~ week, data = example)
## 
## Residuals:
##       Min        1Q    Median        3Q       Max 
## -0.099294 -0.039929 -0.005938  0.032715  0.169885 
## 
## Coefficients:
##             Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&amp;gt;|t|)    
## (Intercept) 0.100161   0.005261  19.039   &amp;lt;2e-16 ***
## week        0.004087   0.002563   1.595    0.112    
## ---
## Signif. codes:  0 &amp;#39;***&amp;#39; 0.001 &amp;#39;**&amp;#39; 0.01 &amp;#39;*&amp;#39; 0.05 &amp;#39;.&amp;#39; 0.1 &amp;#39; &amp;#39; 1
## 
## Residual standard error: 0.05562 on 214 degrees of freedom
##   (9 observations deleted due to missingness)
## Multiple R-squared:  0.01174,    Adjusted R-squared:  0.007124 
## F-statistic: 2.543 on 1 and 214 DF,  p-value: 0.1123&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;within-person-models-e.g.-2-level-models&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Within person models e.g., 2-level models&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We saw this last time where we can think of everyone being run in a seperate regression model. Here the lines connect the dots of the same people across time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(tidyverse)
gg2 &amp;lt;- ggplot(example,
   aes(x = week, y = SMN7, group = ID)) + geom_point() + stat_smooth(method = &amp;quot;lm&amp;quot;, se = FALSE)   

gg3 &amp;lt;- gg2 +  stat_smooth(data = example, aes(x = week, y = SMN7, group=1, colour=&amp;quot;#990000&amp;quot;), method = &amp;quot;lm&amp;quot;, size = 3, se=FALSE) + theme(legend.position = &amp;quot;none&amp;quot;)
print(gg3)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Lectures/03-Growth-curves_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-4-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each person has multiple assessments, so we need to distinguish between people and their assessments. In normal regression we wouldn’t think about this as everyone datapoint is assumed to be independent. However, this is not the case here. Failing to distinguish would lead to violation of independence, an important assumption of the standard regression model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As seen in the graph above, what we have now is both individual level slopes as well as an average level slope. The average level slope is going to be the average of the individual level slopes, which will look like our average slope ignoring all dependencies. Same for the intercept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to do this is to run seperate regressions for each person. Then we could just pool (or average) together where people start and how much they change to get the average intercept (starting value) and trajectory (how much people change). We will see later that this is a somewhat poor approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Joining, by = &amp;quot;ID&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;regressions &amp;lt;- example2 %&amp;gt;% 
  group_by(ID) %&amp;gt;% 
  do(tidy(lm(SMN7 ~ week, data = .)))

head(regressions)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## # A tibble: 6 x 6
## # Groups:   ID [3]
##   ID    term        estimate std.error statistic  p.value
##   &amp;lt;fct&amp;gt; &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt;          &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;     &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;     &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;    &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;
## 1 67    (Intercept)  0.0921    0.0161       5.72   0.0292
## 2 67    week         0.00662   0.00657      1.01   0.420 
## 3 75    (Intercept)  0.126   NaN          NaN    NaN     
## 4 75    week         0.00771 NaN          NaN    NaN     
## 5 87    (Intercept)  0.0787  NaN          NaN    NaN     
## 6 87    week        -0.0227  NaN          NaN    NaN&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the average intercept and the average trajectory there is also the amount of variation around each of these estimates. Do people tend to change the same? Are there individual differences in the initial assessment?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This type of meaningful variation is lost when we have a between subjects only model that ignores the individual level. This variation will be called Random Effects (or variance estimates in SEM).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Side note: note how some people do not have se estimates for their regression coefficients. The reason for this will impact our ability to fit longitudinal models later on.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is another important source of variation different from standard regression models. The within-subjects error that can be seen in the below graph. If we did not take people into account and just collapsed across people to get a between subjects assessment of change, this error would be confounded with individual differences in change. We will discuss this error more in depth later, but one way to think about our goal is to utilize our repeated assessments to make better predictions. A way to do that is to create additional buckets of explained variance, resulting in a smaller bucket of unexplained variance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;example3 &amp;lt;- example2 %&amp;gt;% 
  filter(ID == &amp;quot;67&amp;quot;) &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;gg4 &amp;lt;-  ggplot(example3, aes(x = week, y = SMN7, group = ID)) +  geom_point() + stat_smooth(method = &amp;quot;lm&amp;quot;)

gg4&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Lectures/03-Growth-curves_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-8-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;thinking-about-random-effects&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Thinking about random effects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;random-effects&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Random effects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within subjects variability in either starting value or slope/trajectory is referenced in terms of random effects. How do we represent this in our equation? Easy, we just say that the typical regression parameters we have are not the same for everyone – that they are random (in contrast to fixed).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, when would we want to use random effects? If there is some sort of selection (random or not) of many possible values of the predictor (e.g., stimuli are 3 random depression drugs, three semi random chosen levels of a drug). With longitudinal data this is (random) people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Side bar: Even in situations where these levels are not random (eg working with states) it is still useful to use MLM and we still call them random effects. To be consistent with language, random here can refer to as random from the population average, not randomly selected. When talking about “random effects” you can mean either of these defintions (and a few more). Luckily we can mostly ignore these semantic issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is necessary for modeling random effects? For longitudinal models, there needs to be multiple assessments per your grouping category (people, schools, neighborhoods, trials).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are assuming these random effects are sampled from some population and thus vary from group to group (or person to person). This means that your coeffients (like traditional regression coefficients) are estimates of some population parameter and thus have error associated with them. This error is not like like a standard residual, which represents error for your overall model. Nor is it like the standard error for a point estimate. Random effects can best be thought of as deviation of individual regression lines from the group regression line (though it technically is not this).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To facilitate the multiple assessments per person we will now use both i and j subscripts. We will see that the random effects are part of the overall error term in the model. Counterintutitively, the main focus of these types of models will be the fixed effects, with less attention paid to the random effects. That said, the random effects are necessary to account for dependency in the data. One can think about these models as normal fixed effects regressions, with the random effects there to account for the longitudinal nature of the data. They are made up of a number of standard regression equations, each for a single individual. Doing so side steps the trouble of having correlated errors, and thus allows us to interpret our findings without concern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To faciliate adding random effects to our model it is helpful to think about two “levels” to our regression equation. We are going to put a regression equation within our requestion equation. (Que Xzhibit joke). The first level will be the within-person model, in that it described how people differ across time. The second level will be the between person level. Note that these do not correspond to fixed or random effects. Instead they can be thought to model either within person differences or between person differences. Mastering thinking at these two levels will help make sense of these MLM models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;empty-model-equation&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Empty model equation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the most basic model and then expand from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Level 1 - within person
&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ {Y}_{ij} = \beta_{0j}  +\varepsilon_{ij} \]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that we have multiple responses per individual j, noted with an i to refer to specific times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also note that the intercept has a subscript. In typical regression it does not. This suggests that not everyone has the same intercept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The residuals at this level are thought of as measurment error OR as something that can be explained by time varying predictors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Level 2 - between person
&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ {\beta}_{0j} = \gamma_{00} + U_{0j} \]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Level 2 takes the intercept (or other parameter) at level 1 and breaks it down into an equation for each individual, j. An overall group average (the gamma) and a residual term specific to deviation around the intercept (see below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And two variance components:
1. a random effect of the intercept
&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ {U}_{0j} \sim \mathcal{N}(0, \tau_{00}^{2})  \]&lt;/span&gt;
The subscript of the &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(U_{0j}\)&lt;/span&gt; refers to the number of the parameter where 0 is the intercept, 1 is the first regression coefficient, and so on. The second refers to the individual, j. So &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(U_{0j}\)&lt;/span&gt; refers to the intercept whereas &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(U_{1j}\)&lt;/span&gt; would refer to the random effect of the first regression coefficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(U_{0j}\)&lt;/span&gt; random effect is said to be normally distributed with a mean of zero and a variance of &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\tau\)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the residual error term
&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ {R}_{ij} \sim \mathcal{N}(0, \sigma^{2})  \]&lt;/span&gt;
Much like in normal regression there is an error term for all of the variation we cannot account for. What is unique here is that we took that normal variation and split it into two components. One that is attributable to variation around the intercept &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\({U}_{0j}\)&lt;/span&gt; and a catch all residual.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technically this is not a growth model, nor one that is inherently longitudinal. However, it does serve as a nice starting point to identify random effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;putting-it-together&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Putting it together&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ {Y}_{ij} = \gamma_{00} + U_{0j}  + \varepsilon_{ij} \]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;visualize-what-you-are-doing&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Visualize what you are doing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine the raw data plotted without knowing person j, how would &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\varepsilon_{i}\)&lt;/span&gt; be calculated?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now think about the data plotted again but with knowing each person has their own intercept. How would &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\varepsilon_{ij}\)&lt;/span&gt; be calculated?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, how is U_{0j} calculated?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;icc&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;ICC&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ICC:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[\frac{U_{0j}}{U_{0j}+ \varepsilon_{ij}}\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is defined as % variation between vs within person variance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;adding-time&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Adding time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the basic growth model where our predictor is a time variable&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Level 1:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ {Y}_{ij} = \beta_{0j}  + \beta_{1j}X_{ij} + \varepsilon_{ij} \]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note how similar this looks like to a normal regression equation. Again, the differences are due to those pesky subscripts. Like before, think of this as a normal regression equation at the level of a person. Each person would have one of these equations with, in addition to a unique Y, X and residual, a unique &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\beta_{0}\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\beta_{1}\)&lt;/span&gt;. Look above to those individaul regressions we did at the start of this section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Level 2:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ {\beta}_{0j} = \gamma_{00} + U_{0j}\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Level 2 takes the parameters at level 1 and decomposes them into a fixed component that reflects that average and then the individual deviations around that fixed effect. &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(U_{0j}\)&lt;/span&gt; is not error in the traditional sense. It describes how much variation there is around that parameter. Do some people start higher while some start lower, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ {\beta}_{1j} = \gamma_{10} \]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new level 2 term refers to the first predictor in the level 1 regression equation ie the slope. This slope is fixed in that the level 2 equation only has a gamma term and no U residual term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Putting it together:
&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ {Y}_{ij} = \gamma_{00} + \gamma_{10} (X_{1j})+ U_{0j}  + \varepsilon_{ij} \]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that in computing a single individuals Y, it depends on the two fixed effects, the Xj, and the random effect for the intercept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-does-this-look-like-graphically&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What does this look like graphically?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And how does this differ from the random intercept model?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does this look like graphically?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can you draw out the sources of error? The random effects for each participant? The fixed effects?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;adding-a-random-slope&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Adding a random slope?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happens when we add a random slope?
Level 1:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ {Y}_{ij} = \beta_{0j}  + \beta_{1j}X_{1j} + \varepsilon_{ij} \]&lt;/span&gt;
Level 2:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ {\beta}_{0j} = \gamma_{00} + U_{0j}\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ {\beta}_{1j} = \gamma_{10} + U_{1j} \]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ {Y}_{ij} = \gamma_{00} + \gamma_{10}(X_{ij})+ U_{0j} + U_{1j}(X_{ij}) + \varepsilon_{ij} \]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can think of a persons score divided up into a fixed component as well as the random component.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These random effects are likely related to one another. For example, if someone starts high on a construct they are then less likely to increase across time. This negative correlation can be seen in the residual structure, where the random effects are again normally distributed with a mean of zero, but this time one must also consider covariance in addition to variance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ \begin{pmatrix} {U}_{0j} \\ {U}_{1j} \end{pmatrix}
\sim \mathcal{N} \begin{pmatrix} 
  0,     &amp;amp; \tau_{00}^{2} &amp;amp; \tau_{01}\\ 
  0, &amp;amp; \tau_{01} &amp;amp; \tau_{10}^{2}
\end{pmatrix} \]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that it is possible to have a different error structure, one where there is no relationship between the intercept and the slope. We will discuss this more later in the semester. Right now just know that the default is to have correlated random effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also have the within subject variance term that accounts for deviations that are not accounted for by time variable and other level 1 predictors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ {R}_{ij} \sim \mathcal{N}(0, \sigma^{2})  \]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that it is possible to model these level 1 residuals with different structures. This specification implies that there is no correlation across an individuals residuals, once you account for level 1 predictors (ie growth trajectories). Having a specific level 1 autoregressive or other type of pattern is common in other treatments of longitudinal models (panel models) but is not necessary with growth models (but possible).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the basic format of the growth model. It will be expanded later on by adding variables to the level 1 model and to the level 2 model. Adding to the level 1 model is only possible with repeated variables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Level 1 regression coefficients are added to the level 2 model. These coefficients are decomposed into a fixed effect, a random effect (possibly), and between person predictors. As with any regression model, each of these only have a single error term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;individaul-level-random-effects&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Individaul level random effects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;calculation-of-individaul-level-random-effects&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Calculation of individaul level random effects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Random effects are often thought in terms of variance components. We can see this if we think of individual level regressions for each person where we then have a mean and a variance for both the intercept or the slope. The greater the variance around the intercept and the slope means that not everyone starts at the same position and not everyone changes at the same rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to look at a specific person’s random effect you can think of it as a deviation from the fixed effect where subject 6’s intercept can be thought of as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ {\beta}_{06} = \gamma_{00} \pm U_{06}\]&lt;/span&gt;
e.g 2.2 = 3 - .8&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;how-are-these-random-effects-calculated&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How are these random effects calculated?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It isn’t as straightforward as calculating a slope for each person and then using the difference between that slope and the average slope. Instead, the estimates are partially pooled towards the overall mean of the sample, the fixed effect. We do this to get a better estimate of the parameters, the same way that using regression to predict y-hat given an X is better than binning X and calculating y-hat. More information = better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why not full pooling? Because it ignores individaul differences in change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is that the variance of the change trajectories (using MLM) will be smaller than the variance of the fitted linear models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;random-effects-and-residual-standard-assumptions&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;random effects and residual (standard) assumptions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joint normal distribution of random effects&lt;br /&gt;
Normally distributed residual&lt;br /&gt;
Constant variance over time&lt;br /&gt;
Random effects and residual are uncorrelated&lt;br /&gt;
Both have a mean of zero&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Random effects and residual size will depend on predictors in the model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;random-effect-decomposition&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Random effect decomposition&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of the original total variance in a scatter plot of our DVs. Adding random effects takes that variance and trims it down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The intercept only MLM seperates it into a level 1 variance (which at this stage is treated as error) and a level 2 random intercept variance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating a random slopes model takes the Level 1 residual variance and creates a new “pile” of explained variance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;working-with-models-in-r&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;working with models in R&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;data-analysis-and-data-structures&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Data analysis and data structures&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;wide-and-long-form&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Wide and Long form&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on what type of analysis you want to perform you may need to restructure your data. I recommend the combination of tidyr and dplyr (among others) to restructure and manage your dataframes. The first decision you need to make is whether you want your data structured in a long or a wide format. There are multiple names to refer to these two types: multivariate vs univariate, person-level vs person-period, etc but they all refer to the same idea. How to structure your data depends on both what level of analysis (individual, dyad, household) and what type of analyses (MLM/SEM). Typically our focus is on individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wide form is common among non-longitudinal data. It has one line per individual with all of their repeated measures in the same row, each with some name to distinguish which assessment wave the data came from. In general, this format is used for SEM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## # A tibble: 3 x 4
##      ID ext_1 ext_2 ext_3
##   &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;
## 1     1     4     4     4
## 2     2     6     5     4
## 3     3     4     5     6&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, long format has a row per observation. Thus, participants likely have many rows, each one referring to a different assessment wave. There are fewer variables in this format which makes organization somewhat easier. Thus this has been referred to as “Tidy” data. Graphing with ggplot is facilitated when using tidy data such as being in the long format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## # A tibble: 9 x 3
##      ID  time   ext
##   &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;
## 1     1     1     4
## 2     1     2     4
## 3     1     3     4
## 4     2     1     6
## 5     2     2     5
## 6     2     3     4
## 7     3     1     4
## 8     3     2     5
## 9     3     3     6&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you go back and forth? We use the tidyr package! As of a few months ago, you would use the gather and the spread functions. Now these are being phased out and are being replaced by pivot_longer and pivot_wider. The functions work similar but the newer ones are a little more intuitive both in terms of remembering the correct function name as well as well adding more bells and whistles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gather and pivot_longer goes from wide to long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(tidyr)

wide_to_long &amp;lt;- wide %&amp;gt;% 
  gather(ext_1:ext_3,key = &amp;quot;time&amp;quot;, value = &amp;quot;ext&amp;quot;) 
wide_to_long&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## # A tibble: 9 x 3
##      ID time    ext
##   &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;
## 1     1 ext_1     4
## 2     2 ext_1     6
## 3     3 ext_1     4
## 4     1 ext_2     4
## 5     2 ext_2     5
## 6     3 ext_2     5
## 7     1 ext_3     4
## 8     2 ext_3     4
## 9     3 ext_3     6&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(tidyr)

wide_to_long.p &amp;lt;- wide %&amp;gt;% 
  pivot_longer(-ID, names_to = &amp;quot;time&amp;quot;, values_to = &amp;quot;ext&amp;quot;) 
wide_to_long.p&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## # A tibble: 9 x 3
##      ID time    ext
##   &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;
## 1     1 ext_1     4
## 2     1 ext_2     4
## 3     1 ext_3     4
## 4     2 ext_1     6
## 5     2 ext_2     5
## 6     2 ext_3     4
## 7     3 ext_1     4
## 8     3 ext_2     5
## 9     3 ext_3     6&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note the similarities. The key in all three is to 1. identify which columns need to be reshaped. Here is it all of them besides ID. 2. we need to name the newly created variable that consists of the old column names (here time). 3. we need to name what those values represent (here levels of extraversion)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The separate function could be used to get only the assessment wave number. This might be useful when combining data together or for creating a common time metric for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;wide_to_long2 &amp;lt;- wide_to_long %&amp;gt;% 
  separate(time, into = c(&amp;quot;omit&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;wave&amp;quot;), sep = &amp;quot;_&amp;quot;, convert = TRUE) %&amp;gt;%
  dplyr::select(-omit) %&amp;gt;% 
  arrange(ID)
wide_to_long2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## # A tibble: 9 x 3
##      ID  wave   ext
##   &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;int&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;
## 1     1     1     4
## 2     1     2     4
## 3     1     3     4
## 4     2     1     6
## 5     2     2     5
## 6     2     3     4
## 7     3     1     4
## 8     3     2     5
## 9     3     3     6&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Note that the seperate function will identify non numeric characters and use that to seperate the values. You can omit the sep = function to check yourself. &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One issue that comes up here is that we have differing dates for each assessment. Ideally we would like to utilize that extra information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## # A tibble: 3 x 7
##      ID ext_1 ext_2 ext_3 date_1 date_2  date_3 
##   &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt;  &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt;   &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt;  
## 1     1     4     4     4 1/1/10 5/1/10  8/1/10 
## 2     2     6     5     4 1/6/10 4/10/10 9/1/10 
## 3     3     4     5     6 1/8/10 4/25/10 9/13/10&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do we fix it? The same way we would with multiple variables we want to convert. Wave, along with ID helps us keep track of what variables go with which person at which time. Together, the two serve as a unique identifier. To better understand the code go through each line to see what the intervening data frame looks like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;long.date &amp;lt;- wide.date %&amp;gt;% 
  gather(-ID, key = &amp;quot;time&amp;quot;, value = &amp;quot;value&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;% 
  separate(time, into = c(&amp;quot;variable&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;wave&amp;quot;)) %&amp;gt;% 
  spread(variable,value) 
long.date&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## # A tibble: 9 x 4
##      ID wave  date    ext  
##   &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt; &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt;   &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt;
## 1     1 1     1/1/10  4    
## 2     1 2     5/1/10  4    
## 3     1 3     8/1/10  4    
## 4     2 1     1/6/10  6    
## 5     2 2     4/10/10 5    
## 6     2 3     9/1/10  4    
## 7     3 1     1/8/10  4    
## 8     3 2     4/25/10 5    
## 9     3 3     9/13/10 6&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One difficulty of creating a wave variable is whether or not the variables are named in a manner such that 1) assessment wave is easily identifiable (e.g. does _a always refer to the first wave whereas _b always refer to the second?) and 2) if that is consistent across variables. Having a wave identifier for your variables is important/necessary. Having an easily selected one (ie at the end of the variable name, hopefully separated by an underscore or a period). If assessment wave separators are embedded within the variable name it will be harder to covert your data. Often, variable data is attached at the end of a name such as SWB_4 to refer to the fourth item in a scale. This may obscure wave identification as in SWB_A_4. A similar naming problem can occur with multiple reports e.g,. SWB_4_parent. I recommend putting wave identification last. The difficulties become partly moot when working in long format (read: entering data in) as opposed to wide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the above code we used spread to go from long to wide as a means of creating a long dataset where there were multiple variables. Technically this is not a tidy dataset in that it comprises of both long and wide information, but it is the typical format used for MLM analyses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going from long to wide uses spread or pivot_wider function. We will utilize this when converting our MLM models to SEM models, but try the code below to see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;long_to_wide &amp;lt;- long %&amp;gt;% 
  spread(time, ext)
long_to_wide&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## # A tibble: 3 x 4
##      ID   `1`   `2`   `3`
##   &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;
## 1     1     4     4     4
## 2     2     6     5     4
## 3     3     4     5     6&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that this is technically the dataframe format that we want. The problem is that our variable names are numeric. This often causes problems. When working with tibbles use backticks ’ to refer to the column e.g., select(‘1’)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;basic-lmer-code&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;basic lmer code&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic function we will work with is lmer from the lme4 package&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(lme4)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Loading required package: Matrix&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## 
## Attaching package: &amp;#39;Matrix&amp;#39;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## The following objects are masked from &amp;#39;package:tidyr&amp;#39;:
## 
##     expand, pack, unpack&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The package was developed to be similar to the lm function. The code will be similar to the formula for the combined model&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code for empty model&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;lmer(Y ~ 1 + (1 | subjects), data=example)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Level 1
&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ {Y}_{ij} = \beta_{0j}  +\varepsilon_{ij} \]&lt;/span&gt;
Level 2
&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ {\beta}_{0j} = \gamma_{00} + U_{0j} \]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Combined
&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ {Y}_{ij} = \gamma_{00} + U_{0j}  + \varepsilon_{ij} \]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 is the way to reference the intercept. All additional fixed effects go outside the parentheses. Inside the parentheses are the random effects and residual terms. To the right of the vertical line is our level 1 residual term, which references the grouping variable. In this case, as with almost all longitudinal work, is the subject ID. To the left of the vertical line is the random effects we want to estimate. Right now this estimates only one random effect, one for the intercept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is possible to suppress a random intercept by putting a zero instead of a 1. If you do not put anything there the 1 is implied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;lmer(y ~ 1 + time + (1 + time | subjects), data=data)

lmer(y ~ time + (time | subjects), data=data)
# both are equivalent&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;example&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Example&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;mod.1 &amp;lt;- lmer(SMN7 ~ 1 + (1 | ID), data=example)
summary(mod.1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Linear mixed model fit by REML [&amp;#39;lmerMod&amp;#39;]
## Formula: SMN7 ~ 1 + (1 | ID)
##    Data: example
## 
## REML criterion at convergence: -714.1
## 
## Scaled residuals: 
##     Min      1Q  Median      3Q     Max 
## -2.1575 -0.4728 -0.0232  0.4512  3.2750 
## 
## Random effects:
##  Groups   Name        Variance Std.Dev.
##  ID       (Intercept) 0.001823 0.04270 
##  Residual             0.001302 0.03608 
## Number of obs: 225, groups:  ID, 91
## 
## Fixed effects:
##             Estimate Std. Error t value
## (Intercept) 0.106972   0.005106   20.95&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;how-to-calculate-icc&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How to calculate ICC?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;0.001823/(0.001823 + 0.001302)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## [1] 0.58336&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;exploring-beyond-the-summary&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Exploring beyond the summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;class(mod.1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## [1] &amp;quot;lmerMod&amp;quot;
## attr(,&amp;quot;package&amp;quot;)
## [1] &amp;quot;lme4&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-do-the-random-effects-look-like&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;what do the random effects look like?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(sjPlot)
plot_model(mod.1, facet.grid = FALSE, 
          sort = &amp;quot;sort.all&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning in min(new_value, na.rm = T): no non-missing arguments to min;
## returning Inf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning in min(dat$conf.low): no non-missing arguments to min; returning
## Inf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning in min(dat$estimate): no non-missing arguments to min; returning
## Inf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning in max(dat$conf.high): no non-missing arguments to max; returning -
## Inf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning in max(dat$estimate): no non-missing arguments to max; returning -
## Inf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning in min(ticks): no non-missing arguments to min; returning Inf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning in max(ticks): no non-missing arguments to max; returning -Inf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Lectures/03-Growth-curves_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-23-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best Linear Unbiased Predictor = BLUP. More on this later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;head(ranef(mod.1))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## $ID
##       (Intercept)
## 6   -0.0597240676
## 29  -0.0101119688
## 34  -0.0103698893
## 36  -0.0035902640
## 37  -0.0082433829
## 48   0.0455797808
## 53  -0.0222710793
## 54  -0.0066548052
## 58  -0.0060624543
## 61  -0.0271347235
## 66  -0.0123359896
## 67  -0.0026491341
## 69   0.0348398944
## 71  -0.0486040243
## 74   0.0484338355
## 75   0.0224228634
## 76  -0.0021583228
## 78   0.0224780927
## 79  -0.0054325535
## 80  -0.0194707993
## 81   0.0712662731
## 82   0.0053695094
## 85  -0.0532215425
## 86  -0.0388885304
## 87  -0.0387411472
## 89  -0.0208712287
## 91   0.0123812011
## 92  -0.0078125821
## 93   0.0430219016
## 94  -0.0543390588
## 96   0.0233440081
## 97  -0.0497003277
## 98  -0.0432302582
## 99   0.0104394983
## 101  0.0508032394
## 102 -0.0104344307
## 103 -0.0206130188
## 104 -0.0482473609
## 105 -0.0478231980
## 106 -0.0028045239
## 110  0.0418641247
## 112 -0.0109089622
## 114 -0.0549314098
## 115 -0.0013505715
## 116  0.0062422910
## 120  0.0300499418
## 122  0.0793976365
## 125  0.0532803435
## 127 -0.0105050866
## 129 -0.0448207025
## 135  0.0406255726
## 136 -0.0364069792
## 137 -0.0444890904
## 140 -0.0153440709
## 141  0.0770651692
## 142  0.0817077387
## 143  0.0072423981
## 144  0.0001680065
## 146 -0.0551006778
## 149 -0.0137965477
## 150  0.0091583792
## 152 -0.0187707293
## 153  0.0490992150
## 155 -0.0233396072
## 156 -0.0218943803
## 159 -0.0488368935
## 160  0.0024524455
## 162  0.0911638809
## 163  0.0155327007
## 165  0.0320764602
## 167 -0.0025217361
## 169  0.0647586755
## 171 -0.0397728293
## 174  0.0259232134
## 182 -0.0154177625
## 187 -0.0581588783
## 189  0.0348767402
## 190 -0.0030744230
## 193  0.0636533019
## 194  0.0099321407
## 201  0.0104848276
## 204  0.0414352908
## 205  0.0353188897
## 208  0.0033367444
## 209 -0.0346144188
## 211  0.0168223034
## 214 -0.0374146988
## 219  0.0564683729
## 222 -0.0262135788
## 223 -0.0228606119
## 229 -0.0484315899&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;head(coef(mod.1))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## $ID
##     (Intercept)
## 6    0.04724795
## 29   0.09686005
## 34   0.09660212
## 36   0.10338175
## 37   0.09872863
## 48   0.15255179
## 53   0.08470093
## 54   0.10031721
## 58   0.10090956
## 61   0.07983729
## 66   0.09463602
## 67   0.10432288
## 69   0.14181191
## 71   0.05836799
## 74   0.15540585
## 75   0.12939488
## 76   0.10481369
## 78   0.12945011
## 79   0.10153946
## 80   0.08750121
## 81   0.17823829
## 82   0.11234152
## 85   0.05375047
## 86   0.06808348
## 87   0.06823087
## 89   0.08610079
## 91   0.11935322
## 92   0.09915943
## 93   0.14999392
## 94   0.05263296
## 96   0.13031602
## 97   0.05727169
## 98   0.06374176
## 99   0.11741151
## 101  0.15777525
## 102  0.09653758
## 103  0.08635900
## 104  0.05872465
## 105  0.05914882
## 106  0.10416749
## 110  0.14883614
## 112  0.09606305
## 114  0.05204060
## 115  0.10562144
## 116  0.11321430
## 120  0.13702196
## 122  0.18636965
## 125  0.16025236
## 127  0.09646693
## 129  0.06215131
## 135  0.14759759
## 136  0.07056503
## 137  0.06248292
## 140  0.09162794
## 141  0.18403718
## 142  0.18867975
## 143  0.11421441
## 144  0.10714002
## 146  0.05187134
## 149  0.09317547
## 150  0.11613039
## 152  0.08820128
## 153  0.15607123
## 155  0.08363241
## 156  0.08507763
## 159  0.05813512
## 160  0.10942446
## 162  0.19813589
## 163  0.12250471
## 165  0.13904847
## 167  0.10445028
## 169  0.17173069
## 171  0.06719918
## 174  0.13289523
## 182  0.09155425
## 187  0.04881314
## 189  0.14184875
## 190  0.10389759
## 193  0.17062532
## 194  0.11690415
## 201  0.11745684
## 204  0.14840730
## 205  0.14229090
## 208  0.11030876
## 209  0.07235760
## 211  0.12379432
## 214  0.06955732
## 219  0.16344039
## 222  0.08075844
## 223  0.08411140
## 229  0.05854042&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;fixef(mod.1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## (Intercept) 
##    0.106972&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do these relate? Lets calculate ID 6 intercept random effect&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#coef = fixef + raneff

# coef for ID = 6 is 0.04724795  
0.106972 -0.0597240676 &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## [1] 0.04724793&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get residuals and fitted scores&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(broom)
example.aug&amp;lt;- augment(mod.1, data = example)


# .fitted    = predicted values
# .resid    = residuals/errors
# .fixed     = predicted values with no random effects&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;adding-time-to-the-mlm&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Adding time to the MLM&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;fixed-slope&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;fixed slope&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;mod.2f &amp;lt;- lmer(SMN7 ~ 1 + week + (1  | ID), data=example)
summary(mod.2f)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Linear mixed model fit by REML [&amp;#39;lmerMod&amp;#39;]
## Formula: SMN7 ~ 1 + week + (1 | ID)
##    Data: example
## 
## REML criterion at convergence: -675.4
## 
## Scaled residuals: 
##     Min      1Q  Median      3Q     Max 
## -2.2308 -0.4868 -0.0377  0.4542  3.2337 
## 
## Random effects:
##  Groups   Name        Variance Std.Dev.
##  ID       (Intercept) 0.001815 0.04261 
##  Residual             0.001300 0.03606 
## Number of obs: 216, groups:  ID, 88
## 
## Fixed effects:
##             Estimate Std. Error t value
## (Intercept) 0.104041   0.005733  18.147
## week        0.001331   0.001755   0.758
## 
## Correlation of Fixed Effects:
##      (Intr)
## week -0.426&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does this look like graphically?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;random-slope&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Random slope&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;mod.2 &amp;lt;- lmer(SMN7 ~ 1 + week + (week  | ID), data=example)
summary(mod.2)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Linear mixed model fit by REML [&amp;#39;lmerMod&amp;#39;]
## Formula: SMN7 ~ 1 + week + (week | ID)
##    Data: example
## 
## REML criterion at convergence: -678.1
## 
## Scaled residuals: 
##      Min       1Q   Median       3Q      Max 
## -1.93345 -0.47015 -0.00405  0.46985  2.67965 
## 
## Random effects:
##  Groups   Name        Variance  Std.Dev. Corr
##  ID       (Intercept) 1.688e-03 0.041085     
##           week        5.999e-05 0.007745 0.11
##  Residual             1.114e-03 0.033378     
## Number of obs: 216, groups:  ID, 88
## 
## Fixed effects:
##             Estimate Std. Error t value
## (Intercept) 0.104719   0.005466  19.157
## week        0.000489   0.001913   0.256
## 
## Correlation of Fixed Effects:
##      (Intr)
## week -0.339&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How does the intercept change from the random intercpet only model? It may change because the intercept is now conditional on time ie after accounting for time. It is not the predicted outcome when time = 0. You can think of the previous intercept as the grand mean of person means. If our week variable here changed across time then there would be a larger change in the intercept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you interpret week?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How did the random effects change?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;why-treating-time-is-so-important&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Why treating time is so important&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time with a different scale. How do we interpret? And what changes?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;example$week.n &amp;lt;- (example$week - 30)
  
mod.2n &amp;lt;- lmer(SMN7 ~ 1 + week.n + (week.n  | ID), data=example)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning in checkConv(attr(opt, &amp;quot;derivs&amp;quot;), opt$par, ctrl =
## control$checkConv, : Model failed to converge with max|grad| = 1.99825 (tol
## = 0.002, component 1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;summary(mod.2n)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Linear mixed model fit by REML [&amp;#39;lmerMod&amp;#39;]
## Formula: SMN7 ~ 1 + week.n + (week.n | ID)
##    Data: example
## 
## REML criterion at convergence: -674.8
## 
## Scaled residuals: 
##     Min      1Q  Median      3Q     Max 
## -2.2053 -0.4841 -0.0423  0.4505  3.2646 
## 
## Random effects:
##  Groups   Name        Variance  Std.Dev.  Corr 
##  ID       (Intercept) 1.001e-03 0.0316327      
##           week.n      1.333e-07 0.0003652 -1.00
##  Residual             1.320e-03 0.0363343      
## Number of obs: 216, groups:  ID, 88
## 
## Fixed effects:
##             Estimate Std. Error t value
## (Intercept) 0.146910   0.050598   2.904
## week.n      0.001432   0.001763   0.812
## 
## Correlation of Fixed Effects:
##        (Intr)
## week.n 0.995 
## convergence code: 0
## Model failed to converge with max|grad| = 1.99825 (tol = 0.002, component 1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;random-effects-1&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Random effects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;calcualtion-of-random-effect-confidence-interval&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Calcualtion of random effect confidence interval&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conveys the predicted range around each fixed effect in which 95% of the sample individauls are predicted to fall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;95% random effect = fixed effect plus minus 1.96 * random standard deviation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to calcualte?
1. Intercept &lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ \gamma_{00} \pm  1.96  *  \tau_{U_{0j}}  \]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;0.1193933 + (1.96 * 0.240217) &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## [1] 0.5902186&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;0.1193933 - (1.96 * 0.240217) &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## [1] -0.351432&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slope &lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ \gamma_{10} \pm  1.96  *  \tau_{U_{1j}}  \]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;0.0004891 + (1.96 * 0.007745) &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## [1] 0.0156693&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;0.0004891 - (1.96 * 0.007745) &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## [1] -0.0146911&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;###Individaul level random effects&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are the intercept random effects the same as the model with only the intercept? Why or why not?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;head(ranef(mod.1))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## $ID
##       (Intercept)
## 6   -0.0597240676
## 29  -0.0101119688
## 34  -0.0103698893
## 36  -0.0035902640
## 37  -0.0082433829
## 48   0.0455797808
## 53  -0.0222710793
## 54  -0.0066548052
## 58  -0.0060624543
## 61  -0.0271347235
## 66  -0.0123359896
## 67  -0.0026491341
## 69   0.0348398944
## 71  -0.0486040243
## 74   0.0484338355
## 75   0.0224228634
## 76  -0.0021583228
## 78   0.0224780927
## 79  -0.0054325535
## 80  -0.0194707993
## 81   0.0712662731
## 82   0.0053695094
## 85  -0.0532215425
## 86  -0.0388885304
## 87  -0.0387411472
## 89  -0.0208712287
## 91   0.0123812011
## 92  -0.0078125821
## 93   0.0430219016
## 94  -0.0543390588
## 96   0.0233440081
## 97  -0.0497003277
## 98  -0.0432302582
## 99   0.0104394983
## 101  0.0508032394
## 102 -0.0104344307
## 103 -0.0206130188
## 104 -0.0482473609
## 105 -0.0478231980
## 106 -0.0028045239
## 110  0.0418641247
## 112 -0.0109089622
## 114 -0.0549314098
## 115 -0.0013505715
## 116  0.0062422910
## 120  0.0300499418
## 122  0.0793976365
## 125  0.0532803435
## 127 -0.0105050866
## 129 -0.0448207025
## 135  0.0406255726
## 136 -0.0364069792
## 137 -0.0444890904
## 140 -0.0153440709
## 141  0.0770651692
## 142  0.0817077387
## 143  0.0072423981
## 144  0.0001680065
## 146 -0.0551006778
## 149 -0.0137965477
## 150  0.0091583792
## 152 -0.0187707293
## 153  0.0490992150
## 155 -0.0233396072
## 156 -0.0218943803
## 159 -0.0488368935
## 160  0.0024524455
## 162  0.0911638809
## 163  0.0155327007
## 165  0.0320764602
## 167 -0.0025217361
## 169  0.0647586755
## 171 -0.0397728293
## 174  0.0259232134
## 182 -0.0154177625
## 187 -0.0581588783
## 189  0.0348767402
## 190 -0.0030744230
## 193  0.0636533019
## 194  0.0099321407
## 201  0.0104848276
## 204  0.0414352908
## 205  0.0353188897
## 208  0.0033367444
## 209 -0.0346144188
## 211  0.0168223034
## 214 -0.0374146988
## 219  0.0564683729
## 222 -0.0262135788
## 223 -0.0228606119
## 229 -0.0484315899&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;head(coef(mod.1))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## $ID
##     (Intercept)
## 6    0.04724795
## 29   0.09686005
## 34   0.09660212
## 36   0.10338175
## 37   0.09872863
## 48   0.15255179
## 53   0.08470093
## 54   0.10031721
## 58   0.10090956
## 61   0.07983729
## 66   0.09463602
## 67   0.10432288
## 69   0.14181191
## 71   0.05836799
## 74   0.15540585
## 75   0.12939488
## 76   0.10481369
## 78   0.12945011
## 79   0.10153946
## 80   0.08750121
## 81   0.17823829
## 82   0.11234152
## 85   0.05375047
## 86   0.06808348
## 87   0.06823087
## 89   0.08610079
## 91   0.11935322
## 92   0.09915943
## 93   0.14999392
## 94   0.05263296
## 96   0.13031602
## 97   0.05727169
## 98   0.06374176
## 99   0.11741151
## 101  0.15777525
## 102  0.09653758
## 103  0.08635900
## 104  0.05872465
## 105  0.05914882
## 106  0.10416749
## 110  0.14883614
## 112  0.09606305
## 114  0.05204060
## 115  0.10562144
## 116  0.11321430
## 120  0.13702196
## 122  0.18636965
## 125  0.16025236
## 127  0.09646693
## 129  0.06215131
## 135  0.14759759
## 136  0.07056503
## 137  0.06248292
## 140  0.09162794
## 141  0.18403718
## 142  0.18867975
## 143  0.11421441
## 144  0.10714002
## 146  0.05187134
## 149  0.09317547
## 150  0.11613039
## 152  0.08820128
## 153  0.15607123
## 155  0.08363241
## 156  0.08507763
## 159  0.05813512
## 160  0.10942446
## 162  0.19813589
## 163  0.12250471
## 165  0.13904847
## 167  0.10445028
## 169  0.17173069
## 171  0.06719918
## 174  0.13289523
## 182  0.09155425
## 187  0.04881314
## 189  0.14184875
## 190  0.10389759
## 193  0.17062532
## 194  0.11690415
## 201  0.11745684
## 204  0.14840730
## 205  0.14229090
## 208  0.11030876
## 209  0.07235760
## 211  0.12379432
## 214  0.06955732
## 219  0.16344039
## 222  0.08075844
## 223  0.08411140
## 229  0.05854042&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;fixef(mod.1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## (Intercept) 
##    0.106972&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do these relate? Lets calculate ID 6 intercept random effect&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#coef = fixef + raneff

# 0.04724795  
0.106972 -0.0597240676 &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## [1] 0.04724793&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get residuals and fitted scores&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(broom)
example.aug&amp;lt;- augment(mod.1, data = example)


# .fitted    = predicted values
# .resid    = residuals/errors
# .fixed     = predicted values with no random effects&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;adding-time-1&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;adding time&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;mod.2 &amp;lt;- lmer(SMN7 ~ 1 + week + (week  | ID), data=example)
summary(mod.2)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Linear mixed model fit by REML [&amp;#39;lmerMod&amp;#39;]
## Formula: SMN7 ~ 1 + week + (week | ID)
##    Data: example
## 
## REML criterion at convergence: -678.1
## 
## Scaled residuals: 
##      Min       1Q   Median       3Q      Max 
## -1.93345 -0.47015 -0.00405  0.46985  2.67965 
## 
## Random effects:
##  Groups   Name        Variance  Std.Dev. Corr
##  ID       (Intercept) 1.688e-03 0.041085     
##           week        5.999e-05 0.007745 0.11
##  Residual             1.114e-03 0.033378     
## Number of obs: 216, groups:  ID, 88
## 
## Fixed effects:
##             Estimate Std. Error t value
## (Intercept) 0.104719   0.005466  19.157
## week        0.000489   0.001913   0.256
## 
## Correlation of Fixed Effects:
##      (Intr)
## week -0.339&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Random effects another way&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;re2 &amp;lt;- ranef(mod.2)
head(re2)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## $ID
##       (Intercept)          week
## 6   -5.657190e-02 -0.0036945459
## 29  -8.481756e-03 -0.0012401120
## 34  -6.559720e-03 -0.0036272361
## 36  -7.107377e-03  0.0047529824
## 37  -7.584156e-03  0.0003779790
## 48   3.760800e-02  0.0079905136
## 53  -1.989445e-02 -0.0015608099
## 54   1.298061e-03 -0.0046572183
## 58   3.763976e-04 -0.0054304028
## 61  -2.523030e-02 -0.0013740463
## 66  -1.692834e-02  0.0022291440
## 67  -4.435808e-03  0.0020525694
## 71  -4.790346e-02  0.0002829010
## 75   2.147451e-02  0.0025670702
## 76  -1.178132e-03  0.0005880005
## 78   1.590422e-02  0.0031440504
## 79  -4.554999e-03  0.0005646937
## 80  -1.789820e-02 -0.0007154790
## 81   5.310404e-02  0.0082155118
## 82   4.163353e-03  0.0008114128
## 85  -5.229368e-02 -0.0013883325
## 86  -3.747004e-02 -0.0020088462
## 87  -3.530494e-02 -0.0042629307
## 89  -1.906497e-02 -0.0008530205
## 91   1.547560e-02 -0.0021933791
## 92  -5.127067e-03 -0.0012825084
## 93   3.779074e-02  0.0055466427
## 94  -5.318192e-02 -0.0005568113
## 96   2.535874e-02 -0.0004379578
## 97  -4.654850e-02 -0.0019515143
## 98  -3.875698e-02 -0.0027541673
## 99   9.785177e-03  0.0016155143
## 101  4.073120e-02  0.0116039230
## 103 -1.910831e-02 -0.0013254022
## 104 -4.656380e-02 -0.0034349757
## 105 -4.532176e-02 -0.0021913974
## 106  4.024883e-05 -0.0015454111
## 110  5.266477e-02 -0.0065630548
## 112 -5.482604e-03 -0.0041413140
## 114 -5.187791e-02 -0.0023737578
## 115 -6.018565e-04  0.0004676209
## 116  7.916722e-03 -0.0002939168
## 120  3.156554e-02  0.0021828094
## 122  7.845607e-02  0.0030220350
## 125  5.565560e-02 -0.0004030572
## 127 -1.035814e-02  0.0009947753
## 129 -4.383714e-02 -0.0011901610
## 135  4.517320e-02 -0.0027851051
## 136 -3.257406e-02 -0.0027536989
## 137 -4.307457e-02 -0.0026649722
## 140 -1.389973e-02 -0.0009470411
## 141  7.828180e-02  0.0011246004
## 142  7.656429e-02  0.0071700560
## 143  8.802167e-03  0.0001782843
## 144  5.023920e-04  0.0007247389
## 146 -5.190868e-02 -0.0030652978
## 149 -1.315714e-02  0.0001913378
## 150  1.329264e-02 -0.0028911814
## 152 -1.719482e-02 -0.0013669192
## 153  4.865193e-02  0.0022929034
## 155 -2.212352e-02 -0.0004931690
## 156 -2.041537e-02 -0.0004522343
## 159 -4.783022e-02 -0.0015435325
## 160  3.459146e-03  0.0001563020
## 162  8.771544e-02  0.0058967120
## 163  1.575853e-02  0.0011486036
## 165  3.244233e-02  0.0013196820
## 167 -5.436807e-04 -0.0009083619
## 169  6.576873e-02  0.0011926808
## 171 -3.475852e-02 -0.0047511867
## 174  2.798144e-02 -0.0004759192
## 182 -5.231973e-03 -0.0081378967
## 187 -5.609959e-02 -0.0019680493
## 189  3.456648e-02  0.0020405469
## 190 -1.620723e-03 -0.0003743333
## 193  5.854085e-02  0.0071786529
## 194  4.241261e-03  0.0066159420
## 201  1.187752e-02 -0.0001340229
## 204  3.799808e-02  0.0055309494
## 205  4.004323e-02 -0.0029413522
## 208  3.040083e-04  0.0043109412
## 209 -3.367017e-02 -0.0004225192
## 211  1.856239e-02 -0.0003192506
## 214 -3.676234e-02 -0.0001666149
## 219  4.541593e-02  0.0143735740
## 222 -1.947934e-02 -0.0063364890
## 223 -1.719018e-02 -0.0051038253
## 229 -4.254994e-02 -0.0060019177&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;random_params &amp;lt;- tidy(mod.2, effect = &amp;quot;ran_modes&amp;quot;)
head(random_params)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##   level group        term      estimate   std.error
## 1   101    ID (Intercept)  0.1454506216 0.018681911
## 2   101    ID        week  0.0120929048 0.006503270
## 3   103    ID (Intercept)  0.0856111110 0.020552331
## 4   103    ID        week -0.0008364205 0.007484617
## 5   104    ID (Intercept)  0.0581556164 0.020564418
## 6   104    ID        week -0.0029459940 0.007471121&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using simulations to get better estimates of confidence around our estimates&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(merTools)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Loading required package: arm&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Loading required package: MASS&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## 
## Attaching package: &amp;#39;MASS&amp;#39;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## The following object is masked from &amp;#39;package:dplyr&amp;#39;:
## 
##     select&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## 
## arm (Version 1.10-1, built: 2018-4-12)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Working directory is /Users/jackson/Box/5165 Applied Longitudinal Data Analysis/ALDA/content/Lectures&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;FEsim(mod.2)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##          term         mean       median          sd
## 1 (Intercept) 0.1044074017 0.1039119381 0.005272623
## 2        week 0.0007611029 0.0006878781 0.001868060&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;re.sim &amp;lt;- REsim(mod.2)
head(re.sim)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##   groupFctr groupID        term         mean       median         sd
## 1        ID       6 (Intercept) -0.056526527 -0.056522578 0.01853652
## 2        ID      29 (Intercept) -0.009124553 -0.008835317 0.02100211
## 3        ID      34 (Intercept) -0.008828907 -0.006406779 0.01971484
## 4        ID      36 (Intercept) -0.007870006 -0.006666001 0.02263088
## 5        ID      37 (Intercept) -0.008727056 -0.008822997 0.01890044
## 6        ID      48 (Intercept)  0.039487607  0.040242941 0.02003504&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can be used to create CIs for each individaul random effect (and fixed effect). What is the confidence interval around person 6’s intercept estimate compared to person 2000 who has 25 repeated measurements?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;caterpillar-plots&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;caterpillar plots&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look through these different methods of getting random effects. Note that they are not all exactly the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;caterpillar plots&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;p1 &amp;lt;- plotREsim(re.sim)
p1&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Lectures/03-Growth-curves_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-44-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;density-of-individaul-random-effects&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Density of individaul random effects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;p1.gg1 &amp;lt;- re.sim %&amp;gt;% 
  filter(term == &amp;quot;(Intercept)&amp;quot;) 

ggplot(p1.gg1, aes(mean)) +
  geom_density()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Lectures/03-Growth-curves_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-45-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;p1.gg2 &amp;lt;- re.sim %&amp;gt;% 
  filter(term == &amp;quot;week&amp;quot;) 


ggplot(p1.gg2, aes(mean)) +
  geom_density()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Lectures/03-Growth-curves_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-46-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;comparing-to-a-standard-linear-model&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;comparing to a standard linear model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;lm.1 &amp;lt;- lm(SMN7 ~ 1 + week, data = example)
summary(lm.1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## 
## Call:
## lm(formula = SMN7 ~ 1 + week, data = example)
## 
## Residuals:
##       Min        1Q    Median        3Q       Max 
## -0.099294 -0.039929 -0.005938  0.032715  0.169885 
## 
## Coefficients:
##             Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&amp;gt;|t|)    
## (Intercept) 0.100161   0.005261  19.039   &amp;lt;2e-16 ***
## week        0.004087   0.002563   1.595    0.112    
## ---
## Signif. codes:  0 &amp;#39;***&amp;#39; 0.001 &amp;#39;**&amp;#39; 0.01 &amp;#39;*&amp;#39; 0.05 &amp;#39;.&amp;#39; 0.1 &amp;#39; &amp;#39; 1
## 
## Residual standard error: 0.05562 on 214 degrees of freedom
##   (9 observations deleted due to missingness)
## Multiple R-squared:  0.01174,    Adjusted R-squared:  0.007124 
## F-statistic: 2.543 on 1 and 214 DF,  p-value: 0.1123&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;other-types-of-models&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Other types of models&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on your DV, you might not want to have a Gaussian sampling distribution. Instead you may want something like a Poisson or a negative binomial if you are using some sort of count data. You can do this somewhat with lme4. However, the BRMS package – which uses Bayesian estimation – has many more possibilities: geometric, log normal, weibull, exponential, gamma, Beta, hurdle Poisson/gamma/negative binomial, zero inflated beta/Poisson/negative binomial, cumulative. Maybe we will fit some of these later in the semester.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;matrix-notation-as-a-way-to-help-understand-what-is-going-on&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Matrix notation (as a way to help understand what is going on)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ y_{i} = X_{i}\beta + Z_{i}b_{i} + \varepsilon_{i} \]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets assume we have four time points. This formula is equivalent to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \begin{bmatrix}
y_{1j} \
y_{2j} \
y_{3j} \
y_{4j}&lt;br /&gt;
\end{bmatrix} +&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\begin{bmatrix}
1 &amp;amp; time_{1j} \
1 &amp;amp; time_{2j} \
1 &amp;amp; time_{3j} \
1 &amp;amp; time_{4j}&lt;br /&gt;
\end{bmatrix}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\begin{bmatrix}
&lt;em&gt;{0} \
&lt;/em&gt;{1} \
&lt;em&gt;{2} \
&lt;/em&gt;{3}&lt;br /&gt;
\end{bmatrix}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;\begin{bmatrix}
1 &amp;amp; time_{1j} \
1 &amp;amp; time_{2j} \
1 &amp;amp; time_{3j} \
1 &amp;amp; time_{4j}&lt;br /&gt;
\end{bmatrix}
\begin{bmatrix}
b_{0j} \
b_{1j} \
\end{bmatrix}&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;\begin{bmatrix}
&lt;em&gt;{1j} \
&lt;/em&gt;{2j} \
&lt;em&gt;{3j} \
&lt;/em&gt;{4j}&lt;br /&gt;
\end{bmatrix} $$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;X is the design matrix for fixed effects
Z is the design matrix for random effects.
&lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\beta\)&lt;/span&gt; is a vector of fixed effects
b is a vector of random effects
&lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\varepsilon\)&lt;/span&gt; is a vector of residual error&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that all are subject specific (j) besides the vector of fixed effects&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The design matrix can be increased with the inclusion of other predictors (See next week)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;model.matrix(mod.2)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##     (Intercept)      week
## 1             1 0.0000000
## 2             1 0.9479452
## 3             1 1.8493151
## 4             1 0.0000000
## 5             1 1.0383562
## 6             1 0.0000000
## 7             1 2.3917808
## 8             1 0.0000000
## 9             1 2.9589041
## 10            1 0.0000000
## 11            1 1.9369863
## 12            1 2.7917808
## 13            1 0.0000000
## 14            1 1.9068493
## 15            1 2.9424658
## 16            1 0.0000000
## 17            1 3.2246575
## 18            1 0.0000000
## 19            1 1.8602740
## 20            1 4.0109589
## 21            1 0.0000000
## 22            1 1.4082192
## 23            1 2.4739726
## 24            1 0.0000000
## 25            1 2.6575342
## 26            1 0.0000000
## 27            1 2.9698630
## 28            1 5.8109589
## 29            1 0.0000000
## 30            1 0.8931507
## 31            1 1.6657534
## 32            1 4.5232877
## 35            1 0.0000000
## 36            1 0.8657534
## 37            1 1.7753425
## 41            1 0.0000000
## 42            1 2.9589041
## 43            1 0.0000000
## 44            1 1.0164384
## 45            1 2.0328767
## 46            1 0.0000000
## 47            1 3.1232877
## 48            1 5.9863014
## 49            1 0.0000000
## 50            1 2.0164384
## 51            1 0.0000000
## 52            1 3.8109589
## 53            1 0.0000000
## 54            1 3.1150685
## 55            1 6.0493151
## 56            1 0.0000000
## 57            1 2.1369863
## 58            1 3.2301370
## 59            1 6.3178082
## 60            1 0.0000000
## 61            1 1.0712329
## 62            1 0.0000000
## 63            1 1.2109589
## 64            1 0.0000000
## 65            1 2.1369863
## 66            1 0.0000000
## 67            1 1.1397260
## 68            1 2.0383562
## 69            1 0.0000000
## 70            1 0.9753425
## 71            1 1.8657534
## 72            1 0.0000000
## 73            1 1.9260274
## 74            1 3.0356164
## 75            1 0.0000000
## 76            1 1.9315068
## 77            1 3.0438356
## 78            1 0.0000000
## 79            1 1.0054795
## 80            1 2.2136986
## 81            1 0.0000000
## 82            1 0.9698630
## 83            1 0.0000000
## 84            1 1.0054795
## 85            1 2.0575342
## 86            1 2.9150685
## 87            1 0.0000000
## 88            1 0.9616438
## 89            1 2.2986301
## 90            1 3.3232877
## 91            1 0.0000000
## 92            1 1.0520548
## 93            1 2.1835616
## 94            1 3.0164384
## 95            1 0.0000000
## 96            1 0.9041096
## 97            1 3.2657534
## 102           1 0.0000000
## 103           1 1.1534247
## 104           1 0.0000000
## 105           1 1.1945205
## 106           1 0.0000000
## 107           1 0.9671233
## 108           1 2.2410959
## 109           1 0.0000000
## 110           1 1.0410959
## 111           1 3.1123288
## 112           1 0.0000000
## 113           1 1.6164384
## 114           1 3.8794521
## 115           1 0.0000000
## 116           1 0.9369863
## 117           1 3.2273973
## 118           1 0.0000000
## 119           1 1.0602740
## 120           1 3.1232877
## 121           1 0.0000000
## 122           1 1.0136986
## 123           1 3.2986301
## 124           1 0.0000000
## 125           1 0.9178082
## 126           1 3.1616438
## 127           1 0.0000000
## 128           1 1.0027397
## 129           1 0.0000000
## 130           1 0.9780822
## 131           1 3.3041096
## 132           1 0.0000000
## 133           1 1.2054795
## 134           1 3.0767123
## 135           1 0.0000000
## 136           1 1.0410959
## 137           1 3.0739726
## 138           1 0.0000000
## 139           1 0.9232877
## 140           1 0.0000000
## 141           1 0.9589041
## 142           1 2.9972603
## 143           1 0.0000000
## 144           1 1.0383562
## 145           1 3.3890411
## 146           1 0.0000000
## 147           1 1.0739726
## 148           1 0.0000000
## 149           1 0.9095890
## 150           1 0.0000000
## 151           1 3.2602740
## 152           1 0.0000000
## 153           1 3.2273973
## 154           1 0.0000000
## 155           1 1.1205479
## 156           1 0.0000000
## 157           1 3.2082192
## 158           1 0.0000000
## 159           1 2.9972603
## 160           1 0.0000000
## 161           1 3.2794521
## 162           1 0.0000000
## 163           1 2.9917808
## 164           1 0.0000000
## 165           1 1.2356164
## 166           1 0.0000000
## 167           1 3.1780822
## 168           1 0.0000000
## 169           1 1.9123288
## 170           1 0.0000000
## 171           1 1.0520548
## 172           1 2.9397260
## 173           1 0.0000000
## 174           1 0.9753425
## 175           1 0.0000000
## 176           1 3.0876712
## 177           1 0.0000000
## 178           1 1.0383562
## 179           1 3.0109589
## 180           1 0.0000000
## 181           1 3.0876712
## 182           1 0.0000000
## 183           1 3.0493151
## 184           1 0.0000000
## 185           1 2.9342466
## 186           1 0.0000000
## 187           1 3.1315068
## 188           1 0.0000000
## 189           1 2.9342466
## 190           1 0.0000000
## 191           1 2.9780822
## 192           1 0.0000000
## 193           1 3.4575342
## 194           1 0.0000000
## 195           1 2.9945205
## 196           1 0.0000000
## 197           1 3.0520548
## 198           1 0.0000000
## 199           1 2.9972603
## 200           1 0.0000000
## 201           1 3.1041096
## 202           1 0.0000000
## 203           1 3.1863014
## 204           1 0.0000000
## 205           1 3.4547945
## 206           1 0.0000000
## 207           1 2.9369863
## 208           1 0.0000000
## 209           1 3.0849315
## 210           1 0.0000000
## 211           1 2.9945205
## 212           1 0.0000000
## 213           1 3.3150685
## 214           1 0.0000000
## 215           1 3.0876712
## 216           1 0.0000000
## 217           1 2.9945205
## 218           1 0.0000000
## 219           1 2.8273973
## 220           1 0.0000000
## 221           1 2.9178082
## 222           1 0.0000000
## 223           1 2.9479452
## 224           1 0.0000000
## 225           1 2.8465753
## attr(,&amp;quot;assign&amp;quot;)
## [1] 0 1
## attr(,&amp;quot;msgScaleX&amp;quot;)
## character(0)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;estimation&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Estimation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maximum likelihood estimation. Uses a likelihood function that describes the probability of observing the sample data as a function of the parameters. Attempts to maximize the function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;REML vs ML&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Differences account for the fact that fixed effects are being estimated simultaously with th variance parameters. REML accounts for uncertainty in the fixed effects before estimating residual variance. REML attempts to maximize the likelihood of the residuals whereas ML the sample data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you use REML you should be careful in testing fixed effects against eachother (more down below)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;testing-significance-adapted-from-ben-bolker&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Testing significance (adapted from Ben Bolker)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods for testing single parameters
From worst to best:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wald Z-tests. Easy to compute. However, they are asymptotic approximations, assuming both that (1) the sampling distributions of the parameters are multivariate normal and that (2) the sampling distribution of the log-likelihood is (proportional to) χ2.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wald t-tests&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Likelihood ratio test.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) or parametric bootstrap confidence intervals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;p-values-are-not-included&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;P values are not included&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Authors are not convinced of the utility of the general approach of testing with reference to an approximate null distribution. In general, it is not clear that the null distribution of the computed ratio of sums of squares is really an F distribution, for any choice of denominator degrees of freedom. While this is true for special cases that correspond to classical experimental designs (nested, split-plot, randomized block, etc.), it is apparently not true for more complex designs (unbalanced, GLMMs, temporal or spatial correlation, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tl;dr: it gets messy with more complex models&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you really want p values&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# library(lmerTest)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;likelhiood-ratio-test&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Likelhiood ratio test&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How much more likely the data is under a more complex model than under the simpler model (these models need to be nested to compare this).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Log Likelihood (LL) is derived from ML estimation. Larger the LL the better the fit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deviance compares two LLs. Current model and a saturated model (that fits data perfectly).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deviance = -2[LL current - LL saturated]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LL saturated = 1 for MLMs (probability it will perfectly recapture data). log of 1 is 0. So this term drops out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deviance = -2LL current model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comparing 2 models is called a likelihood ration test. Need to have:
1. same data
2. nested models (think of constraining a parameter to zero)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Distributed as chi-square with df equal to constraint differences between models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;mod.2r &amp;lt;- lmer(SMN7 ~ 1 + week + ( 1  | ID), data=example)
summary(mod.2r)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Linear mixed model fit by REML [&amp;#39;lmerMod&amp;#39;]
## Formula: SMN7 ~ 1 + week + (1 | ID)
##    Data: example
## 
## REML criterion at convergence: -675.4
## 
## Scaled residuals: 
##     Min      1Q  Median      3Q     Max 
## -2.2308 -0.4868 -0.0377  0.4542  3.2337 
## 
## Random effects:
##  Groups   Name        Variance Std.Dev.
##  ID       (Intercept) 0.001815 0.04261 
##  Residual             0.001300 0.03606 
## Number of obs: 216, groups:  ID, 88
## 
## Fixed effects:
##             Estimate Std. Error t value
## (Intercept) 0.104041   0.005733  18.147
## week        0.001331   0.001755   0.758
## 
## Correlation of Fixed Effects:
##      (Intr)
## week -0.426&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;anova(mod.2, mod.2r)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## refitting model(s) with ML (instead of REML)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Data: example
## Models:
## mod.2r: SMN7 ~ 1 + week + (1 | ID)
## mod.2: SMN7 ~ 1 + week + (week | ID)
##        Df     AIC     BIC logLik deviance  Chisq Chi Df Pr(&amp;gt;Chisq)
## mod.2r  4 -686.93 -673.43 347.46  -694.93                         
## mod.2   6 -685.45 -665.20 348.73  -697.45 2.5248      2      0.283&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;likelihood-tests-for-random-effects&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Likelihood tests for random effects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not listed in the output because it is hard to do this with variances. Remember variances do not have values below zero and thus the distributions get a wonky quickly. Needs mixture distributions (Cannot be easily done with chi square, for example)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can Do anova comparisons, though that falls to many similar problems as trying to do a Wald test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sampling distribution of variance estimates is in general strongly asymmetric: the standard error may be a poor characterization of the uncertainty. Thus the best way to handle is to do bootstrapped estimates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;aic-and-bic&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;AIC and BIC&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AIC (Akaike’s Information Criterion) and the BIC (Bayesian Information Criterion) where “smaller is better.” This is the opposite of LL/Deviance As with the other types, these may give you wonky findings depending on some factors as they are related to LLs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AIC = 2(number of parameters) + (−2LL)
BIC = ln(n)(number of parameters) + (−2LL)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BIC penalizes models with more parameters more than AIC does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;mcmc&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;MCMC&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More on this later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(rstanarm)
library(brms)
library(mcmcsamp)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#library(mcmcsamp)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;bootstraps&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Bootstraps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parametric bootstrap:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;confint(mod.1, method=&amp;quot;boot&amp;quot;, nsim=1000)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Computing bootstrap confidence intervals ...&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## 
## 7 warning(s): Model failed to converge with max|grad| = 0.00326574 (tol = 0.002, component 1) (and others)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##                  2.5 %     97.5 %
## .sig01      0.03437911 0.05119232
## .sigma      0.03201764 0.04051648
## (Intercept) 0.09665970 0.11679542&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;summary(mod.1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Linear mixed model fit by REML [&amp;#39;lmerMod&amp;#39;]
## Formula: SMN7 ~ 1 + (1 | ID)
##    Data: example
## 
## REML criterion at convergence: -714.1
## 
## Scaled residuals: 
##     Min      1Q  Median      3Q     Max 
## -2.1575 -0.4728 -0.0232  0.4512  3.2750 
## 
## Random effects:
##  Groups   Name        Variance Std.Dev.
##  ID       (Intercept) 0.001823 0.04270 
##  Residual             0.001302 0.03608 
## Number of obs: 225, groups:  ID, 91
## 
## Fixed effects:
##             Estimate Std. Error t value
## (Intercept) 0.106972   0.005106   20.95&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# uses SDs of random effects
# sigma = residual standard error&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comparing two models. fit the reduced model, then repeatedly simulate from it and compute the differences between the deviance of the reduced and the full model for each simulated data set. Compare this null distribution to the observed deviance difference.
This procedure is implemented in the pbkrtest package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(pbkrtest)
#pb &amp;lt;- PBmodcomp(mod.2,mod.2r)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;predictions-and-prediction-intervals&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Predictions and prediction intervals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Predict function is deterministic and uses only the fixed effects (i.e. does not include random effects in the predictions). It does not do prediction in the typical sense where you are predicting &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; individual’s scores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simulate is non-deterministic because it samples random effect values for all subjects and then samples from the conditional distribution. Simulation is needed to create true predictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;predictions-and-prediction-intervals-1&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Predictions and prediction intervals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Predict function is deterministic and uses only the fixed effects (i.e. does not include random effects in the predictions). It does not do prediction in the typical sense where you are predicting &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; individuals’s scores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simulate is non-deterministic because it samples random effect values for all subjects and then samples from the conditional distribution. Simulation is needed to create true preditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Short of a fully Bayesian analysis, bootstrapping is the gold-standard for deriving prediction intervals/bands (ie where would a new person score given X), but the time required is typically high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to generate a proper prediction (for either a new person or a new observation within a person), a prediction must account for three sources of uncertainty in mixed models:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the residual (observation-level) variance,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the uncertainty in the fixed coefficients, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the uncertainty in the variance parameters for the random effects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does so by:
1. extracting the fixed and random coefficients
2. takes n draws from the multivariate normal distribution of the fixed and random coefficients (separately)
3. calculates the linear predictor for each row in newdata based on these draws, and
4. incorporates the residual variation&lt;br /&gt;
then:
5. returns newdata with the lower and upper limits of the prediction interval and the mean or median of the simulated predictions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(merTools)
# see also their shiny app: shinyMer(mod.1)
PI &amp;lt;- predictInterval(merMod = mod.2, newdata = example, level = 0.9, n.sims = 100, stat = &amp;quot;median&amp;quot;, include.resid.var = TRUE)
head(PI)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##          fit       upr          lwr
## 1 0.05308144 0.1183545 -0.002075082
## 2 0.03924756 0.1016895 -0.024710060
## 3 0.04589155 0.1067230 -0.027015400
## 4 0.09898652 0.1629507  0.022304816
## 5 0.09481132 0.1548010  0.028729007
## 6 0.09965443 0.1668782  0.041778680&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nice for bringing in confidence bands around your prediction (And we might use this later)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Broom offers the fitted (predicted) values already if you just want to plot your trajectory. But note that these are not typical prediction intervals (what happens if you get a new participant with a certain value of X). The bands fit in ggplot are for predicted &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\mu\)&lt;/span&gt;|X&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Broom offers the fitted (predicted) values already if you just want to plot your trajectory. But note that these are not typical prediction intervals (what happens if you get a new particpant with a certain value of X). The bands fit in ggplot are for predicted &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\mu\)&lt;/span&gt;|X&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;P.gg &amp;lt;- ggplot(example.aug, aes(x= week, y = .fitted)) + geom_point() + stat_smooth(method = &amp;quot;lm&amp;quot;)   

P.gg&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning: Removed 9 rows containing non-finite values (stat_smooth).&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning: Removed 9 rows containing missing values (geom_point).&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Lectures/03-Growth-curves_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-57-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can also explicitly simulate new data (rather than rely on another function to do so), which will be useful for power calculations later. In the simulated data, the subject means are different from the means in the original data because simulate samples by-subject random effect values using the variance components in the fitted model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sim.1&amp;lt;- simulate(mod.2)
head(sim.1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;coefficient-of-determination-equivalents&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Coefficient of determination equivalents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Issue is: should you include or exclude variation of different random-effects terms?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can do a more Psuedo R2 by taking the difference in variance between model 1 and model 2 and deviding it by model 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;E.g,. residual variance in varying intercept model subtracted from growth model devided by intercept only model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;(sigma(mod.1) - sigma(mod.2)) / sigma(mod.1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## [1] 0.07484984&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proportion of variance explained by time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;batch-analyses&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;batch analyses&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can easily do a lot of models simulataniously. You do not need to use for loops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out dplyr::do as well as purrr::map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;##Now you try:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Graph by hand what an empty model, showing at least two people’s raw data points and describign different sources or error.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1.Run linear models on all of your subjects (a basic regression). What is the average intercept, the average slope?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now run a mlm/lmer model with only a random intercept. What is the ICC? What does residual variance look like compared to linear model? Create a graph to show this effect.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Introduce a fixed slope term. What is the difference in terms of the fixed effects estimates between this estimate and the previous? Of the residual standard error? Create a graph to show both fixed effects estimates and the CIs around them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Run an additional model with a random slope. How does this change compare to the previous model? Should you keep the random slope or not?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Interpret the correlation between the slope and the intercept.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Create a density plot of the random effects from your final model.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Create a catepilar plot of the random effects. Is there any person that seems odd in terms of a large standard errors around intercept and slope estimates?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Create a plot of the trajectory, along with a spaghetti plot of each person’s individual slope. Set the alpha level (transparency) on the individual slopes to make them easier to see.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Create a plot of the trajectory, along with a spagehtti plot of each person’s individual slope. Set the alpha level (transperancy) on the individual slopes to make them easier to see.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 3</title>
      <link>/lectures/2019-08-14-lecture-3-test/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/lectures/2019-08-14-lecture-3-test/</guid>
      <description>



</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
